<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer, or confutation of divers errors broached, and maintained by the seven churches of Anabaptists contained in those articles of their confession of faith propounded to the Parliament, and other grosse opinions held by them against the cleare light of the gospell. By Thomas Bakewell. Imprimatur John Downham.</title>
            <author>Bakewell, Thomas, b. 1618 or 19.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77726</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B526</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E336_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200810</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861448</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861448</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113584</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77726)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113584)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 55:E336[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer, or confutation of divers errors broached, and maintained by the seven churches of Anabaptists contained in those articles of their confession of faith propounded to the Parliament, and other grosse opinions held by them against the cleare light of the gospell. By Thomas Bakewell. Imprimatur John Downham.</title>
                  <author>Bakewell, Thomas, b. 1618 or 19.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20, 25-46, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Shepheard and William Ley, and are to be sold at the signe of the Bible in Tower-Streete, and at Pauls-Chaine neare Doctors Commons.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May: 7th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anabaptists --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113584:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER, <hi>OR</hi> CONFVTATION OF Divers <hi>Errors</hi> Broached and Maintained By the Seven <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>ANABAPTISTS</hi> Contained in thoſe Articles of their <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> Preſented to the PARLIAMENT, and other groſſe Opinions held by them againſt the cleare light of the GOSPELL.</p>
            <p>By THOMAS BAKEWELL.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 TIM. 3.8, 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Now as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo do theſe alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the truth: men of corrupt mindes, reprobate concerning the faith. But they ſhall proceede no further: for their folly ſhall be manifeſt unto all men, as theirs alſo was.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur</hi> John Downham.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Shepheard</hi> and <hi>William Ley,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Signe of the Bible in <hi>Tower-Streete,</hi> and at <hi>Pauls-Chaine</hi> neare <hi>Doctors Commons.</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:113584:2"/>
            <head>The Contents of this Boooke.</head>
            <list>
               <label>CHAP. I.</label>
               <item>THis Chapter containes a confutation of many errours, mentioned by the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in their Articles of faith, defended againſt me by one of their Teachers.</item>
               <label>CHAP. II.</label>
               <item>This Chapter containes other wicked errours of the <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> mentioned againſt me: Firſt, that the bodies of men conſiſting of fleſh and bones, is their ſoules, and that they have no other: Secondly, that the breath of men and beaſts is their ſpirits, and that it is immortall, and liveth when their bodies are dead: Thirdly, they hold that in the Reſurrection, the bodies both of men and beaſts ſhall riſe againe, and their breath ſhall be againe infuſed into them.</item>
               <label>CHAP. III.</label>
               <item>This Chapter containes wicked errours, mentioned againſt me by the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts:</hi> who hold an Univerſall Redemption by Chriſt; if not of beaſts, as was mentioned in the former Chapter, yet of all men although they be already in hell torments.</item>
               <label>CHAP. IV.</label>
               <item>In this Chapter, they hold it unlawfull to uſe that Prayer of Chriſt, <hi>Math.</hi> 6.9. as a Prayer, by the godly, and the ungodly; with a briefe confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that errour.</item>
               <label>CHAP. V.</label>
               <item>This Chapter containes a diſputation, with the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> about the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates power, in commanding thoſe of a contrary judgement, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme in publicke worſhip, or to puniſh them in caſe of refuſall.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113584:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader, The Apoſtacy of others ſhould be as a warning to us: that as we have ſet our hand to the plow of profeſſion, we may not looke backe. Luke. <hi>17.</hi> but goe on unto perfection, and preſſe toward the marke, and for the joy that is ſet before us, we ſhould endure the Croſſe, and runne with patience the race that is ſet before us: and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver turne to the right hand nor to the left, but goe on tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the narrow gate, along the ſtraight way to <hi>Zion,</hi> with our forces thitherward: and encourage our hearts to the Lord by that everlaſting Covenant, that ſhall never be forgotten: and we ſhall obtaine if we faint not; the end of our faith, ſhall be the ſalvation of our ſoules; if we hold out to the end, we ſhall be ſaved; being faithfull to the death we ſhall have the Crowne of life; then I ſay Good Reader take heede of Apoſtacy, doe not beginne in the ſpirit, and then end in the fleſh: for then your former righteouſneſſe ſhall never be remembred; but for your ſinne you ſhall dye: but to thoſe that perſevere in the way of righteouſneſſe, all their former ſinnes ſhall be forgiven, and never remembred more, but they ſhall be caſt into the bottome of the ſea, and blotted out of the book of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and they ſhall be eſteemed as perfectly righteous, having no ſpot nor wrinckle nor any ſuch thing; then keepe thy garments, for thou must walke with Chriſt in robes made white in the blond of the Lambe: pure religion will keepe thee from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpotted by the world; and that thou mayeſt ſo doe, keepe thy ſelfe from the fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the world, yea from both ſcandalous and erroneus perſons: doe not inquire, ſaying, how doe they ſerve their Gods, <hi>Deut. 12.31?</hi> Come not among any erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius perſons. <hi>Iſrael</hi> living amongſt them ſoone learned their workes. <hi>Pſal. 110.35.</hi> enter not into their paths, goe not with with wicked men, avoyde it, paſſe not by it, turne from it, and come away. <hi>Prov. 4.14, 15.</hi> If they ſay, loe here is Chriſt or there, beleeve them not: for there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets, that if it were poſſible, would deceive the very elect. Wherefore if they ſay, behold he is in the deſart, goe not forth, behold he is in the ſecret chambers, beleeve it not. <hi>Math. 24.24.26.</hi> If they preach any other Goſpell, then that the former Saints have beene taught, let them be accurſed. Their new Lights is but Satans deluſion, when he transforms himſelfe into an Angel of light. The old way is the good way, our Fathers walked therein, and were not confounded. <hi>Pſal. 22.44.</hi> Then if
<pb facs="tcp:113584:3"/>they bring not this doctrine, receive them not into thy houſe, nor bid them God ſpeede. <hi>3 Jon. 3.10.</hi> Pertake not of other mens ſinnes, keepe thy ſelfe pure, and he not carried about with every winde of doctrine, The ſlight of men, and cunning craftineſſe whereby they lie in waite to deceive with fairs words. They deceive the hearts of the ſimple, and carry away captive unſtable ſoules into deſtruction: then it is a good thing the heart be eſtabliſhed with grace. Be ye rooted and built up in Chriſt, and ſtand faſt againſt all the wiles of the divell: be not like the <hi>Athenians,</hi> deſiring to hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, have not itching cares after novelties: labour to have godlineſſe with content, and a ſetled minde upon the truth of the Goſpell, ſo ſhalt thou ſtand in theſe perillous dayes, When iniquity abounds, and the love of many waxes cold: labour to love the truth, and thou ſhalt not be given up to beleeve li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s: labour to doe the will of God, and thou ſhalt know his doctrine whether it be of God: and receive nothing for truth till thou haſt weighed it in the ballance of the Sanctuary: let not thy affections be faſtened on any thing, before thou hast tryed it: receive nothing for the love of men, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons, but ſearch the ſcriptures, and ſee whether thoſe things be ſo, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Paul,</hi> but as he followes <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and if ſinners entice thee, conſent thou not; if they ſay come let us heare ſuch a Tradeſ-man preach, goe not with them, leaſt thou be ſnared to thy deſtruction. Then doe not tempt the Lord, nor preſume of thine owne ſtrength to ſtand in ſuch temptations, but take heede leaſt thou fall: be ever jealous of thine owne heart, for it is deceitfull above all things; keepe it with all diligence, and leane not to thine owne understanding; and if thou deſireſt ſatisfaction in any point in controverſie, acquaint thy Paſtor with it before thou give conſent to any thing new come up, or to walke in a way not caſt up from the ancient pathes, reads this Book, and let the Scripture be thy Judge, and if it ſatisfie thee in any thing, give God the prayſe, and let me be remembred in thy prayers, and I ſhall remaine thine, in all Chriſtian duties to be commanded,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THOMAS BAKEWELL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113584:3"/>
            <head>A CONFUTATION OF Divers <hi>Errors</hi> of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> contained in their ARTICLES of FAITH preſented to the PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I</hi> 
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>This Chapter contains a Confutation of many errors maintained by the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in their Articles of Faith defended againſt me, by Mr. <hi>Spilsbury</hi> one of their Teachers.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>heir firſt Article they beleeve, that there is one rule of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for all Saints in all places to be obſerved, of which I doubted: his anſwer was that the ſcripture is that rule to trie and judge all things.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, the ſcripture is an eternall rule of righteouſneſſe, but not commanding the ſame things to be obſerved by all Saints in all times, and in all places. The <hi>Jews</hi> were commanded many things which we are not, and yet by the Scriptures; and we are commanded many things here that ceaſe at our death, and ſhall not be done in heaven: then the ſame things are not to be obſerved by all Saints in all places. Againe if the ſcripture be a rule for all Circumſtances in all duties that make for outward decency and uniformity; Then I muſt ſee a rule for theſe things before <hi>I give my faith to this Article.</hi> In their next article they beleeve that all who know God and Chriſt ſhall have eternall life, but vengeance ſhall be rendered on all that know not God and Chriſt: but here I doubt they exclude
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113584:4"/>all Infants that dye in their Infancy from ſalvation, becauſe they are not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of ſuch knowledge of God and Chriſt. You anſwer ſaying you know not what is this knowledge, neither hath the ſcripture revealed any ſuch that were ſaved. But was not <hi>Jereboams</hi> child ſaved, when the Lord himſelfe ſaid that there was ſome good thing in him towards the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 14, 15. And did <hi>David</hi> rejoyce that his childe was damned, and did he deſire to goe to hell to his childe and rejoyce in beleeving it. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.23. And why ſhould not Infants that dye be ſaved, when as they may be ſanctified, which is eternall life begunne already? and they may be ſanctified as well as <hi>Jeremiah</hi> and <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt. <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.15. Then, are you a teacher and know not theſe things? but you ſay you will not judge them, when as you make it an article of your faith to beleeve that none ſhall be ſaved with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this knowledge of God in Chriſt, which infants are not capable of; yet they may have the ſeeds of grace in them wrought by the Spirit of God: neither can this be denyed, when as they are ſanctified by the Spirit of God. Againe if I ſhould beleeve this Article, I feare I ſhould condemne many of Gods people, which have the faith of adherence, but not the faith of evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: for many that live a holy life, may want a cleare evidence that God is reconciled to them in Chriſt, therefore <hi>I dare not give</hi> my faith to beleeve this Article.</p>
               <p>Your ſixteenth article is this, you beleeve that unleſſe Chriſt had beene God he could not perfectly have knowne the will of God, which I doubt of: but you anſwer that you beleeve that Chriſt was both God and man and the Prophet that all muſt heare: but what of this? who doubts of it? but then you ſay that you will decline what the Word of God doth not hold forth: but I feare you will not be as good as your word, but ſuppoſe you be; yet how doth this ſatiſfie my doubt? Yet further I grant that no crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can fully know this ſecret will of God: for Chriſt as man knew not when the day of Judgement ſhould be. <hi>Mark.</hi> 13.32, Neither can one crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture know what God hath revealed to all creatures. Man doth not know what God hath revealed to Angels, nor doe they know fully what God hath revealed to men, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. neither doth one man know what God hath revealed to the ſoule of another: yet all this hinders not but Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels glorified, although they be but creatures, doe perfectly know what Gods will is to them, and their duty to him: then if you beleeve this article, that Chriſt had not perfectly knowne the will of God, but that he was God: Why then doe you ſay that you will beleeve no more than the Word holds forth? The VVord ſaith although here we ſee but darkely, as through a glaſſe or latiſee, yet then we ſhall ſee face to face, and know as we are knowne, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12. and yet creatures ſtill, not Godded with God nor Chriſted with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113584:4"/>Chriſt, and yet we ſhall perfectly know his will to us, and our duty to him. Then if you be as good as your word, you muſt caſt away this Article <hi>of your faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The twentieth article, you beleeve that the Kingdome of Chriſt ſhall then be perfected, when Chriſt ſhall come the ſecond time, and reigne amongſt his Saints; Here I doubt you beleeve that the Kingdome of Chriſt ſhall then be perfected, when Chriſt ſhall come from heaven perſonally into this world before the end of it, and raigne: Monarchically here on earth a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares. Your anſwer is that Chriſts Kingdom ſhall then be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, when Gods will is accompliſhed in the ſame: and that Chriſt by the brightneſſe of his appearing ſhall effect it; but in what ſpace of time, you know not. I anſwer, Gods will cannot be accompliſhed till all his decrees are fulfilled, which cannot be before the day of Judgement: then ſhall all things that offend be gathered out of his Kingdom, and caſt into the furnace of fire <hi>Math.</hi> 13.40, 41, 42. Then after the diſſolution of all things ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> we according to his promiſe look for new heavens and a new earth, wherein dwelleth righteouſneſſe, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. then indeede what <hi>Adam</hi> loſt ſhall be reſtored by Chriſt the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> to its firſt purity, and then the Saints ſhall inherit all things, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.1.7. For the new heavens and the new earth which I will make, ſhall remaine before me ſaith the Lord, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66.22. then the Kingdomes and Dominions under the whole Heavens ſhall be given to the Saints of the Moſt High, whoſe Kingdome is an everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Kingdome, and all Dominions ſhall ſerve and obey Chriſt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.27. and of his Kingdom there ſhall be no end. <hi>Luke.</hi> 1.33. But the heaven ſhall receive Chriſt till the reſtitution of all things to their firſt perfection, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.21. then this article is not by the ſcripture held forth; therefore I dare not give my faith unto it.</p>
               <p>The five and twentieth article, you beleeve that the tenders of the Goſpell are abſolutely free and no way requiring, as neceſſary the preceding miniſtry of the Law, or any qualifications or preparations wrought by it: but onely that the naked ſoule as a ſinner and ungodly, to receive Chriſt crucified, dead and buried, riſen and made a Prince and a Saviour for ſuch a ſinner. But I doubt of this, and you anſwer that you know nothing abſolutely neceſſary to ſave man, but Jeſus Chriſt and him crucified, and faith to beleeve and apply the ſame: but is not the Word of God a neceſſary Inſtrument in the hand of Chriſt, whereby he workes faith in us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10, 17? by which we beleeve in Chriſt: then is not the VVord of God neceſſary to ſave where it is, although God is able to worke faith in his elect without it in places where it is not, but this being the orrdinary way for our ſalvation, and while this laſteth, we muſt not ſeeke any extraordinary way: then you ſay the way that God ſaves
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113584:5"/>men, you will leave to him, and every mans experience, when as you make it an article of your faith to beleeve that the Law of God can be no inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall meanes to worke any qualifications, as the Law to fit the ſoule for the ſeeds of grace: when as three thouſand witneſſes by experience were pricked by the Law in one place. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. before the Goſpell was applied to cure them, and multitudes more in ſcripture; beſides every godly mans owne experience; but your conſcience hath forced you to renounce this article, and inſtead of beleeving it, you leave it to every mans <hi>owne experience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſeven and twentieth article, you beleeve that the three Perſons in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, are made over to Chriſtians in their fulneſſe; but I ſuppoſe they have no more of God then a finite creature is able by the weake hand of faith to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive. According to thy faith be it unto thee, <hi>Math.</hi> 8.13. But you anſwer God makes knowne his grace and good will to man in Chriſt by his Spirit, ſo farre as he pleſeth: but who doubts of this, but I ſuppoſe we are not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to receive the fulneſſe of God, we have but our meaſure according to the gift of Chriſt. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4 7 13. neither doe we receive the fulneſſe of Chriſt, <hi>but out of his fulneſſe we receive, Iohn</hi> 1.16.</p>
               <p>The nine and twentieth article, you beleeve that thoſe which are beleevers are in truth really; ſeparated both in ſoule and body from all ſinne through the bloud of the everlaſting Covenant; but I much doubt of this; you anſwer that you beleeve all ſinne is ſo taken away by Chriſt that it ſhall never hinder the ſalvation of any beleever; but this is not my doubt; then you ſay for a beleever to have no ſinne, while he lives in the fleſh, that you deny, and ſo have caſt away this article of your faith: in which you have publiſhed to the world that you beleeve that every beleever is really ſeparated from all ſinne both in body and ſoule by the bloud of Chriſt: then for ſhame doe not carry one face in private, and another <hi>publickcly to the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The three and thirtieth article you beleeve that Chriſt hath a ſpirituall Kingdome here on earth, which is his Church that he hath purchaſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed: but this I grant; then you beleeve that this purchaſed redeemed Church of Chriſt is viſible, and a company of Saints called and ſeparated from the world by the VVord and Spirit of God to the viſible profeſſion of faith, and the Goſpell, and baptized in the faith, and joyned to the Lord, and to each other by a mutuall agreement in practicall enjoyment of the Ordinances commanded by Chriſt their Head and King; but I much doubt of theſe things, then you anſwer ſaying you beleeve that the Church of Chriſt is a purchaſed people called to their viſible profeſſion of him; and for inviſible things you leave to God till he make them viſible. But here all men may ſee the falſeneſſe of your faith; for when you ſhould bring it into the preſence of God, then you leave it. but how dare you publiſh to the world that thoſe whom Chriſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113584:5"/>hath purchaſed and redeemed, are viſible, making profeſſion of faith and the Goſpell, and baptized and joyned to the Lord, and to each other in the practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call injoyment of the Ordinances? When as know I put you to it, you dare not ſtand to it, but you will leave it to God, and ſo you caſt away this article al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: and I thinke if I ſhould goe to all whoſe hands are at them, they would ſhuffle in the ſame manner, and I would wiſh you to take them to helpe you; and ſo if you can prove all the redeemed of Chriſt to be ſuch: I am ſure he ſaith himſelfe other ſheepe I have which are not of this fold, them I muſt bring in, <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.16. then are all viſible and called, and already make profeſſion? &amp;c. Nay, thoſe that are in the ſtate of grace are not ſo viſible; for that white ſtone and that new name written, no man knowes but he that hath it, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.17. they are called hidden ones, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.3. and the Lord had ſeven thouſand which the Prophet knew not of, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.18. And ſometimes the Saints themſelves in the viſible Church may diſagree: Witneſſe <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas, Gen.</hi> 15.7. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.39. and then the cruelty of this article ſhewes from whence it came, which condemnes all that are not in your Church, to be reprobates: then I cannot blame you for leaving it to God, when you are queſtioned for it; but if your heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne you, take heede of <hi>hypocriſie,</hi> God is greater then your heart and knoweth all things, 1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.21.</p>
               <p>The foure and thirtieth article, you beleeve that to this viſible Church all are bound to come, and acknowledge Chriſt to be their King Prieſt and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and to be enrouled amongſt his houſhold ſervants: now this I grant, if you mean the univerſali inviſible Church: but I much doubt whether it ought to be ſo in yours, or in any viſible Church, but you anſwer that you know not how any can be either Sonnes or Servants of God that are not of his houſhold; this I grant to be true in the inviſible Church; but as I proved before, all are not viſible; ſo then their names ought to be written in heaven, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.20 but not written amongſt your company, then you ſay that you are ignorant of any inviſible Church or Houſe of God; I anſwer, Ignorance will not excuſe your ſinne, for Chriſt is the Head of the body or Church, both of things viſible and inviſible, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.16, 17. then although you know not the Church of the firſt borne in which the ſoules of juſt men are made perfect, yet you may know that there is ſuch a one, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. and although the Saints departed know not what is done in the viſible part of the Church here, as the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 63.16. will this prove that there is no ſuch thing? Againe, if you know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the Church, but what is viſible to all, you plainely ſhow your ſelfe to be an hypocrite. For ſpirituall things are ſpiritually diſcerned, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. there is foode which you know not of, you have not taſted of that hidden Manna, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.32. and while your name is at thoſe articles, you
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113584:6"/>want that inward grace of faith to beleeve them, and ſo cannot ſee like <hi>Moſes</hi> him that is inviſible, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.27.</p>
               <p>The ſixe and thirtieth article; You beleeve that every particular Church hath power to chuſe for themſelves meete perſons into office, and none other have power &amp;c: but I doubt of it; you anſwer either the Church or the World muſt chuſe them, and which it is let the Scripture be judge: this I grant that the Church repreſentative or the Presbytery ſent <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> to <hi>Samaria Acts</hi> 8.14. and <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> another way. <hi>Chap</hi> 13.3. but no man never did labour to gather to himſelfe a Church, neither did any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation ſeparate themſelves from the reſt, and claime this power to chuſe officers out of their owne company, but they brought them to the Apoſtles to ordaine them, and to appoint or authorize them to their office. <hi>Acts.</hi> 6.3.6. The Apoſtles laboured to gather diſciples to the multitude, having all an Intereſt in it, as a common Presbytery: ſo then there never was any ſingle Congregation governed by it ſelfe, though you make it an article <hi>of your faith to beleeve it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſeven and thirtieth article; You beleeve that you may take one of your ſheepe and make him your ſhepherd; but I doubt of it; you anſwer that you know not where the Saints ſhould find a Paſtor, if not among Church members: but this I grant, for we muſt chuſe a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> &amp; not a <hi>Iew</hi> or a <hi>Turke</hi> to be our Miniſter, and we muſt take him out of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and ſo we doe when we take them out of the Schools of the Prophets, the Univerſities: for a Trades-man is placed by God otherwiſe, and a man without humane lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ought not to meddle in it: it is none of his buſineſſe, and hee ought not to meddle with other mens matters; yet here you make it an article of your faith to beleeve that your Congregation may take one of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and make him their Paſtor. I grant that we may take a man of our coaſts, and ſet him up for a watchman. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.2. But for you to take a ſheep of your owne flocke, and make him your ſhepheard, having no ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but from his fellow-ſheepe: you have <hi>no foundation in the ſcripture for this article of your faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The eight and thirtieth article; You beleeve that the Miniſters maintenance muſt be a voluntary contribution: but I doubt of it; your anſwer is, that all acceptable ſervice to God ought to be free, whereof his ſervants maintenance is a part. I anſwer, it is true, although the Miniſters wages ſhould be certaine, yet it ſhould be given freely: and ſo we ſhould freely pay all other debts; and although it ought to be certaine yet this hinders not but we may be willing and doe it freely: and ſo ſay this is a ſervice to God I ſay it is no more to God then all other duties of the ſecond table of the Law are: which are to be done to men in conſcience of obedience to God that commands it. But the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113584:6"/>argument why the ſeven Churches will give the Miniſter what they liſt, is this becauſe it was <hi>Philemons</hi> voluntary contribution, if he did any thing for his man <hi>Oneſimus</hi> that had brake covenant with him and was ran away from him, and <hi>Paul</hi> intreates him to uſe him kindely, <hi>Phil.</hi> 14.18. But what is this to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery? Will it follow becauſe a ſervant hath broke covenant, and is run away from his Maſter, and now what he doth for him is voluntarily, that therefore a Congregation may do ſo with their faithfull Paſtor that abideth with them? Yet I confeſſe if a Paſtor ſhould doe with his flocke, as <hi>Oneſimus</hi> did with his Maſter, be unfaithfull and runne away from them: then let him ſtand to their voluntary contribution; then here is but a weake foundation for this article.</p>
               <p>The nine and thirtieth article; You beleeve that baptiſme muſt be diſpenſed onely to perſons profeſſing faith, to diſciples that are taught: but this I doubt of; you anſwer ſaying you beleeve all that Chriſt commanded, and his ſervants preached, to be truth in Gods worſhip, which was to baptize ſuch as beleeve; but I ſay the Command of Chriſt was not to baptize them that beleeve, but it was to teach, baptizing all Nations; and his ſervants practiſe was, if the chiefe in any houſe beleeved Chriſt to be the Sonne of God, they baptized all the family without any exception of Infants or ſervants; for baptiſme is the preſſe-money before they enter into the Chriſtian warefare, it is a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians colors; then ſhall any profeſſe himſelfe a ſouldier for Chriſt, before he hath received his colours, or his preſſe-money? it were preſumption for any to doe it, and it is for want of wit in thoſe that deſire it; ſo then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing is rather after then before baptiſme, unleſſe you would have the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of Chriſt fight their warfare, and then afterwards come <hi>for their preſſe-money.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fortieth article; You beleeve that this Ordinance muſt be diſpenſed by dipping or plunging; which I doubt of; you anſwer what Chriſt commands ought to be done without doubting; this I grant; but then you ſay that Chriſt commanded to baptize by plunging; but I cannot finde it; <hi>therefore I dare not give my faith to this article.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The one and fortieth article, You beleeve that the perſons deſigned by Chriſt to diſpenſe this Ordinance, are not officers in the Church onely, but teaching Diſciples; this I doubt of; but you anſwer that a Diſciple; did baptize but you know no officer except a Deacon that did baptize: yet you deny not but they may; but doe you not know that <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle baptized <hi>Criſpus,</hi> and the houſhold of <hi>Stephanus</hi> and the Jailor, and all his? But whoſe Diſciple was he? and the Deacon you ſpeake of. I ſuppoſe to be <hi>Philip,</hi> but he was called to be an Evangeliſt, and then he baptized the eunuch. <hi>Acts.</hi> 8.21. It is there ſaith that he was one of thoſe Deacons, not that he is one ſtill; then
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113584:7"/>your ſeven Churches would prove that Diſciples may baptize from theſe ſcriptures. <hi>Math.</hi> 26.26.28. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.17. <hi>John</hi> 4.12. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7. But what if Chriſt called his Apoſtles Diſciples in relation to his owne Perſonall Miniſtery? will it follow that he ſent them out Diſciples? if ſo, then hee ſent them out to be taught, and baptized of all Nations; but Chriſt ordained twelve, and ſent them out to preach, and they were called Apoſtles before he ſent them out. <hi>Mark.</hi> 3.14 6.30. <hi>Luke</hi> 6.13. But then he ſought for baptiſme in the old Teſtament, and there he found that God ſaith, binde the teſtimony and ſeale of the Law among my Diſciples. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 8.16. I anſwer, if God binde the Law and ſeale the teſtimony among his Miniſters, then how dare theſe men to meddle with their Office? The Preiſts lippes muſt keepe knowledge, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.7. The Law ſhall not periſh from the Preiſt, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſonnes ſhall keepe the Preiſts office, <hi>Numb.</hi> 1.50.53.18.1. Then by this proofe all but Miniſters are barr'd from touching thoſe holy things: then how dare theſe men to meddle with that Office, unleſſe they were called of God, and ſo lawfully placed in it?</p>
               <p>The two and fortieth article, you beleeve that the power to caſt out, and to receive in, lies in the whole body of the Congregation: but I doubt you meane the execution of it, which is to be inflicted not by all, but by many. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.3. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. and ſo they are to admit of Infidels when they become Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: but thoſe that are already baptized neede not ſuch <hi>admittance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The three and fortieth article; You beleeve that a particular Church muſt trie their Officers gifts, and then they may preach publickely, and take upon them the charge of a Paſtor: but I doubt of it; your anſwer is, that when Chriſt gives ability to any, they ought to improve it for their Maſters advantage; but I ſay it muſt be alſo in that place where their Maſter ſets them, or elſe they doe it for their owne advantage, and not for his. but you ſay, if they be found falſe, your Churches will not be corrupted by them: but I ſay if children be left fatherleſſe, and have none to take care of them, they will ſoone be corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and to ſay that you will not be corrupted, and yet uſe no meanes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve your ſelves, is but preſumption; like <hi>Peter</hi> who ſaid that he would not deny his Maſter, and yet tarried in the High Prieſts hall: ſo your Church will not be corrupted, and yet you take away thoſe that are appointed to keepe <hi>you from corruption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſixe and fortieth article, you beleeve that none muſt ſeparate from a Church rightly conſtituted for corruptions that are in it: but if you doe not diſſemble, you make it an article of your faith to beleeve your <hi>ſelves to be Schiſmatickes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The nine and fortieth article; You beleeve that you are bound to yeelde ſubjection to all civill Lawes made by the King and Parliament, <hi>and yet you daily oppoſe Government.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:113584:7"/>
               <p>The two and fiftieth article; you beleeve that you have a conſcience voyde of offence, both towards God and towards man, when as you caſt off Gods Law in the worke of converſion, Article 25, and mans law in Eccleſiaſticall things; Witneſſe your ſetting up Churches without their authority: theſe be your articles of faith; then you ſaide you would beleeve all that is written by the Prophets and Apoſtles, deſiring to diſclaime all hereſies and opinions which are not after Chriſt. But I charged you upon this promiſe of your owne, and upon your generall promiſe, together with your ſeven Churches, to be as good as your word, and not to diſſemble in the very articles of your faith: but when I had waited the full time appointed, and ſaw no anſwer come, I went to know the cauſe of it, and he told me flatly that he would never write more unto me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Behold greater Abominations the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> maintained againſt me, That the bodies of men conſiſting of fleſh and bones, is their Soules, and that they have no other. Secondly, that the breath of men and beaſts is their ſpirits, and that it is immortall and liveth when their bodies are dead. Thirdly, They hold that in the reſurrection the bodies both of men and beaſts ſhall riſe againe, and their breath ſhall be infuſed againe into them.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>TO theſe things I anſwer, Firſt, That man hath two natures, the one a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine or ſpirituall ſubſtance like that of Angels adorned with divine facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as the Underſtanding, Judgement, Reaſon, Will, Affection and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; the other part of man is humane being made of the foure Elements as all mortall creatures are, and what caſualties befall a beaſt may befall a man, and man hath no preheminence above a beaſt, <hi>for all is vanity, Eccle.</hi> 3.19. but the ſoule, ſpirit, or heart of a Man, that divine thing may be bound in the bundle of life, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.29. being uncorruptible, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.4. ſo then when the corruptible body dies the ſpirit depart from it, and returnes to God that gave it, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.7. Therefore when the Scripture calls this divine thing a Spirit diſtinctly, it is for the moſt part to be underſtood of thoſe principall faculties of it, as the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, Reaſon and Judgement, <hi>This is the ſpirit of your mind, Epheſ.</hi> 4.23. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Spirit ſearcheth all things, yea the deepe things of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. And when the Scripture diſtinctly calleth this divine thing the Heart, it is to be underſtood the Conſcience, <hi>If thy heart condemne thee, God is greater,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Davids heart ſmote him,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.10. <hi>The Law written in the Heart or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, Rom.</hi> 2.15. And when that divine thing is called the Soule diſtinctly, it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113584:8"/>is to be underſtood the Will and all the affections; ſaith <hi>Paul, We were willing to have parted unto you our owne ſoules becauſe you were deare unto us,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Hannah powred out her ſoule before the Lord,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.15. Yet when that divine thing is called by any of thoſe names, it is to be underſtood the whole inward man; although ſometimes Spirit ſignifies the principall ruling faculties, and by Soule is meant the Will and Affections that are to be regulated by them; and ſo here is meant the Conſcience as an officer in truſt to ſee that this divine order be kept within us, yet for ſubſtance it is the ſame thing, although decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by ſeverall faculties of it.</p>
               <p>Now I ſhall prove that this divine thing, the ſoule, ſpirit or heart of man, is not the body conſiſting of fleſh and bones; firſt, from the immediate cauſes from whence they came, and they differ thus; we have fathers of the fleſh, and we give them reverence; but God alone is the father of ſpirits. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9. <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.22.27.16. then although the fathers of our fleſh begot our bodies, yet ſaith the Lord, all ſoules are mine, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.4. for he formed the ſpirit of man within him, <hi>Za<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h.</hi> 12.1. and he gave it. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.7. then the ſoule is not the body.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the ſoule and body differ when they returne out of the world; then the body returnes to duſt from whence it came, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.19. and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit or ſoule returnes to God that gave it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, when the ſeparation is made, the body dyes; for it is appointed for all men once to dye. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. We muſt needes dye all, and be as water ſpilt upon the ground. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.14. but after death to Judgement. When the body is dead, the ſpirit of man goes upward. <hi>Ecceſ.</hi> 3.20, 21. to a particular Judgement; Then this living ſoule, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7. this incorruptible heart of man goes before the Judge, and receives either the ſentence of abſolution, or of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, while the body is dead; and at the reſurrection, when the bodies of all are raiſed, and made capable to receive their finall eſtate, then they ſhall be brought before the Judge to have the ſentence paſſed upon them for it; then if the ſoule can live and receive judgement, when the body is dead, then the ſoule is not the body.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the body lives no longer then the ſoule is in it: for when the ſoule of the childe was gone, the body lay dead; but when the ſoule came into him againe, the Prophet ſaid, ſee thy ſonne liveth. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 17.20, 21, 22, 23. but to this they ſay, the childes ſickneſſe was ſo ſore, that there was no breath left in him. <hi>ver</hi> 15. therefore ſay they, it was not the ſoule but breath returned. I anſwer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is plaine that the ſoule was gone, and came againe at the prayer of the Prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it is ſaid the breath was gone, which was the ſigne that the ſoule was gone, that they might the better beleeve it; but that breath being gone, returned not againe, but vaniſhed: but the ſoule returning
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113584:8"/>and acting in the childe, cauſed new breath which was never in the childe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; therefore the ſoule is not the body.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, If man can kill the body, and cannot kill the ſoule, then the ſoule is not the body: but Chriſt ſaith, feare not them that can kill the body, and cannot kill the ſoule, <hi>Math.</hi> 10.28. then the ſoule is not the body. But they ſay that <hi>Joſhuah</hi> killed all the ſoules in <hi>Mackedah,</hi> and in <hi>Libnah,</hi> and all the ſoules in <hi>Laciſh, Eglon,</hi> and in <hi>Hebron, Joſh.</hi> 10.30.32.35.37. Therefore the ſoule may be killed, and every living thing hath a ſoule, <hi>Job.</hi> 12.10. which may be killed or dye. I anſwer, theſe places are thus to be underſtood, the vitall or principall part of humane life was ſtone dead, for their better encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the reſt of their enemies which ſhould be killed in like manner, and ſhould never trouble them more, when their vitalls or humane life is ſtone dead. But they ſay our ſoule is bowed downe to the duſt. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.25. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſoule muſt turne to duſt, and be buried in the grave; for ſaith <hi>David, Thou wilt not leave my ſoule in grave, Pſal.</hi> 16.10. I anſwer, it was but <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> vitalls of humane life was almoſt gone, and muſt returne to duſt, and be buried in the grave. As the vitalls and ſpirit of a beaſt goes downeward, ſo muſt his. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.21. onely the ſpirit or vitalls of a beaſt ſhall abide there; but our vitalls of the body ſhall be raiſed againe, and not left in the grave for ever: but the ſoule that divine thing may be in glory, when the body lyes dead. As the ſoules of Chriſt and the theife were in Paradiſe, when their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies were dead on the Croſſe, <hi>Luke.</hi> 22.43. the ſoules of <hi>Abraham Iſaach</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> were living when their bodyes were dead. <hi>Math.</hi> 22.32. and the ſoules of them that are ſlaine for the word of God, are in white robes of glory, and crie how long wilt thou not avenge our bloud on them, that dwell on the earth. <hi>Revel.</hi> 6.9, 10, 11. But they ſay, thoſe ſoules, is meant, their bloud cried, as <hi>Abels</hi> bloud did, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>I anſwer <hi>Cains</hi> ſinne in ſpilling that bloud cried for vengeance; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine theſe ſoules that crie, ſpeake of their bloud, ſaying our bloud; but if the bloud had cried. it would have ſaid how long will it be ere thou avenge me: and they are called ſoules, but their bloud was not their ſoules: unleſſe when a man hath loſt ſome bloud, they affirme that he hath loſt ſome part of his ſoule; or ſo many drops ſo many ſoules; then if the ſoule can live when the body is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aine, then the ſoule is not the body. But then they ſay, <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> begot ſo many ſoules of ſuch a wife, and ſo many ſoules went downe into <hi>Egypt. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> 46.22.25, 26 27. I anſwer thoſe that went to <hi>Egypt</hi> are called ſoules from the better and more noble part of man, that divine thing in them; but <hi>Jacob</hi> begot but the vitals of humane life, and no more, as I ſhewed before, being onely a father of their fleſh, but God alone is the father of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits: thus you ſee how they differ in <hi>their</hi> originall cauſe or diſcent, and alſo unto what they returne.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:113584:9"/>
               <p>Now I ſhall ſhew that the ſoule is not the body, by differences betwixt them while they remaine together.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the body is the carkaſe, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.29.33. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 13.24, 25. but the ſoule is the hidden man of the heart. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3, 4. his fleſh upon him ſhall be in paine, and his ſoule within him ſhall mourne, <hi>Job.</hi> 14.22. with my ſpirit within me will I ſeeke thee early, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.9. O my ſoule why art thou ſo diſquieted within me? my ſoule is caſt downe within me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.5.6.11. and <hi>Paul</hi> puts both theſe together, ſaying, though our outward man periſh, yet the inward man is renued daily. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16. ſo then if the body be the carkaſe, and the ſoule be ſome divine thing in that carkaſe, as you ſee, both theſe propoſitions are proved, then the ſoule is not the body, but ſome divine thing that is within it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, while the ſoule and body are together, the ſoule may be woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and greived, when the body hath no hurt, nor is in danger of any hurt. They were pricked at the heart, and cut to the heart, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37.7.54. and the Soule of Chriſt was ſorrowfull before any hurt came to his body, <hi>Math.</hi> 26.38. and falſe Prophets ſlay the ſoules of ſome with lyes, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.18, 19. Her ſoule was vexed within her, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 4.27. when her body had no hurt. A wounded ſpirit who can beare? <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.14. then the ſoule is not the body.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the body may be afflicted when the ſoule is not, for in affliction joy aboundeth. They rejoyced that they were counted worthy to ſuffer ſhame for his name, <hi>Acts.</hi> 4. they ſung pſalmes in priſons <hi>Acts.</hi> 16. therefore the ſoule is not the body.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the ſoule and body may be diſtinguiſhed about holy duties; both are required; for ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> glorifying God in your bodies and ſoules, for they are his, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. but ſaith the Lord, They ſit before thee, and heare thy words as my people, when their hearts are gone after their covetouſneſſe, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.31. They draw neare with their lips when their heart is farre from me. <hi>Math.</hi> 15.8. ſo then you ſee the ſoule may be wanting in holy duties when the body is preſent, therefore the ſoule is not the body.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, the ſoule may have ſweete intercourſe with God, when the body is not active in it; <hi>Hannah</hi> prayed, when her lips did not move, and <hi>Moſes</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed acceptably when he ſaide nothing, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.15. and ſo did <hi>Nehemiah, Chap.</hi> 2 14. God hath promiſed to heare the deſires of the heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.4.10.17. When bodily exerciſe profiteth little, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. then the body is not the ſoule.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, to affirme that the body is the ſoule, will cauſe many abſurdities; for then to ſeeke the Lord with all the heart and ſoule is but to bring their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſes to the ordinances, and when God opened <hi>Lyd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a's</hi> heart, it was to open her carkaſe. And when the Lord gives a new heart, it is to give a new car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſe,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113584:9"/>and a broken heart is a broken carkaſe, and a cleane heart is a cleane carkaſe, and the renting of the heart is the renting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the carkaſe: and when the ſoule of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan</hi> was knit to the ſoule of <hi>David;</hi> if he body and ſoule were the ſame thing, it ſeemes their bodies were tyed together, which were miſerable folly for any man to thinke: then I hope this may ſuffice to ſhew that the ſoule is not the body.</p>
               <p>Secondly, they hold that the breath of men and of beaſts is their ſpirits, and that it is immortall, and liveth when their bodies are dead. To this I ſhall doe as before, to prove that their breath is not their ſpirit, and anſwer what they have to ſay to the contrary as I goe along: onely as I ſaid before, that the ſpirit, ſoule or heart of man is for the moſt part meant the ſame thing for ſubſtance, onely by ſpirit ſome times is meant the underſtanding or principle ruling part of that divine thing: and the ſoule is meant the lower parts or leſſe principle, the will and affections which are to be regulated by them, and by the heart is meant the conſcience that officer of the ſoule, which hath a charge to ſee that this Order be kept; yet I ſay, for the moſt part, when any one of theſe is named, all that divine thing is meant: then the breath of man and beaſts is not the ſpirit, I prove by theſe arguments.</p>
               <p>Firſt, mans breath is a vaniſhing thing, his breath is in his noſtrils, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is he to be accounted of? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2 22. It is a winde that paſſeth, and commeth not againe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.39. It was breathed into man, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2 7. the Lord comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the winde to breath, and the breath came into them; But the ſoules of men are created. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.19. God is the Father of the ſpirits of all fleſh, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16 22. and the heart of man is incorruptible, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3, 4 then the vaniſhing breath of men and beaſts is not their ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Secondly, man and beaſt have all one breath, and yet the ſpirit of man goes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and the ſpirit of beaſts goes downewards to the earth. <hi>Eccl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ.</hi> 3.19.20, 21. therefore the breath of men and beaſts is not their ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Job</hi> makes a diſtinction betweene the ſpirit of man and his breath, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if God ſhould ſet his heart on man to gather unto himſelfe his ſpirit, marke, and his breath, <hi>Job.</hi> 34 14. Here is that divine thing, the ſpirit with the ſignes of it which is the breath; then all fleſh ſhall periſh, and turne to duſt, but his ſpirit ſhall returne to God that gave it: and the ſpirits of men and Angels can live in the third heavens above the region of the winds without breath, neither ſhall men when their bodies are made ſpirituall at the reſurrection neede any breath: for it is no part of ſoule or body; and Legions of ſpirits have beene in one man, and yet I ſupoſe he had no more breath then another man, and they might all ſpeake, and yet the man not breath: then I ſuppoſe the breath is but a part of the winde already created infuſed into mortall creatures, while they remaine mortall in this life, and then to returne and never come againe. <hi>Pſai.</hi> 78 39 therefore the breath of men and beaſts is not their ſpirits. But they ſay, <hi>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oure windes are called the foure ſpirits of the heavens. Zach.</hi> 6.5. Hence they conclude that winde or breath in man is his ſpirit. I anſwer, the winde moves the cloudes of heaven, as our ſpirits move us, or as the vitals of beaſts move them, therefore they are called the ſpirits
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113584:10"/>of the heavens: but our breath doth not move us ſo, but rather ſome thing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us moves us, and when our breath goes out, in ſpeaking or otherwiſe, we ſhould dye if we had not ſomething elſe within us to draw it in againe, acting with our vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals: and when that power is gone, we dye. But they ſay, <hi>the body without the ſpirit is dead. Jam.</hi> 2.26. and that (ſay they) is their breath. But if we ſhould grant this, that the body without breath is dead: yet it will not ſo follow that breath is the ſpirit, but that breath is a ſigne of life, or a ſigne that there is a ſpirit in that body, which doth produce that breath. As the fruite of the tree is not the life or ſpirit of the tree, but rather a ſigne that there is life in that tree that doth produce theſe fruits. Then they ſay, <hi>Mans breath of life was breathed into him. Gen.</hi> 2.7. <hi>and when the childes breath was gon, he died.</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 17.17 And if God take away breath from all mortall creatures, <hi>they dye and returne to duſt. Pſal.</hi> 104.27. therefore ſay they, the breath of man and beaſt is their ſpirit. I anſwer as before, it will not follow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſignes of life come and goe with life, that therefore it is life it ſelfe. There be many ſignes of life, as eating, drinking, walking and talking, and when they ceaſe, man dies: yet theſe be but ſignes of life, and ſo is breath in men and beaſts, and therefore it is not their ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, to affirme that the breath in man and beaſts is their ſpirits, many ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities would follow: for they having one breath. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.19. and if this were their ſpirit, then a beaſt may have the ſpirit of wiſedome and knowledge. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11, and the ſpirit of a beaſt might ſearch the deepe things of God as well as the ſpirit of man. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10, 11. and the ſpirit of a beaſt may be wounded. <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.14. and if breath were ſpirit, then God would delight in broken breath. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. and in poore and contrite breath. <hi>Iſay</hi> 66. And if breath be ſpirit, ſome ſhall be borne of breath, and God will give new breath, and all the gifts of the ſpirit would be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but more breath added; and when the ſpirit alſo departed from <hi>Saul,</hi> his breath failed him; and thoſe that ſeparate from the Church, do it becauſe they have not the breath: <hi>Jude.</hi> 19. and <hi>Daniels</hi> excellent gift of the ſpirit, was nothing but a great breath: And when God requires that we ſhould Sing and Pray with the Spirit, he meanes nothing but breath: many more vile abſurdities would follow, if we ſhould be ſo damnably blinde as to beleeve that the breath of men and beaſts is their ſpirit as ſome Anabaptiſts hold.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, they hold that in the reſurrection, the bodies of men and beaſts ſhall riſe againe, and their breath ſhall be infuſed againe into them. To this as to the reſt I ſhall ſhew that the bodies of beaſts ſhall not riſe againe, and for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity anſwer what they have to ſay againſt it, as I goe along.</p>
               <p>Firſt, beaſts have not immortall ſpirits, as I have ſhewed before, unto which their bodies ſhould be againe united, <hi>but their ſpirits are gone downeward to the earth. Eccleſ.</hi> 3.21. Then if theſe beaſts ſhould be raiſed up againe, it would be a new creation of beaſts out of the earth, as they were at the firſt, and could not be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of them from death to life.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the Scripture makes no mention of the reſurrection of beaſts, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113584:10"/>we muſt not be wiſe above that which is written. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. but the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Thou bringeſt man to deſtruction, and ſayeſt returne ye children of men, Pſal.</hi> 90.3. <hi>As in Adam all dye, ſo in Christ ſhall all be made alive, but every man in his order,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.21.22, 23. So then although we beleeve the reſurrection of men, we dare not beleeve the reſurrection of beaſts. But they ſay, <hi>That when the Lord hath take<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the breath of all creatures, and they are dead, and turned to duſt, then he ſends forth his ſpirit, and they are created, and ſo he renues the face of the earth. Pſal.</hi> 104.29, 30. this they ſay is a plaine reſurrection of all the creatures from death to life. I anſwer, Here in this place they are ſaid by the Spirit of God to be created, and ſo in <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. <hi>The Spirit of God moved upon the waters in the work of Creation.</hi> And ſaith <hi>Job, The Spirit of God made me. Job.</hi> 33.4. all this I grant, yet this will not prove a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, unleſſe you make the worke of Creation to be a reſurrection from death to life. But they ſay, this was ſpoken after they were dead, and returned to duſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.29.30. I anſwer, this is frequent in ſcripture: <hi>For things that were done firſt, to be ſet downe laſt.</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.35. There is mention of <hi>Sauls</hi> death, and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muels</hi> mourning for him. and then <hi>Chap.</hi> 17. <hi>Saul conferres with David about his going to fight with Goliah, and afterwards he perſecutes David.</hi> But was all this after his death, becauſe it is ſet downe after it. Againe thou renueſt the face of the earth? this cannot be meant of the reſurrection from death to life: but rather it is to be underſtood an enlarging of ſtrength and comfort after ſome great ſcarcity, with a new ſupply of plenty. But here is nothing concerning reſurrection from death to life.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the Saints of God never expected any reſurrection of beaſts, that ever I read of before theſe <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> but they have alwayes expected a reſurrection of men; for ſaith <hi>Job, Job</hi> 19.25. <hi>When wormes have deſtroyed this body, yet in my fleſh I ſhall ſee God.</hi> And <hi>Martha</hi> ſaith, <hi>I know that he ſhall riſe againe in the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the juſt. Iohn.</hi> 11.24. and ſaith <hi>David, My fleſh ſhall reſt in hope. Pſal.</hi> 16.9. And beſides the Saints in all ages embalmed the dead, and buried them in coffins, and ſepulchers, and cleane linnen, to declare that they expected that they ſhould riſe againe: but I reade of no ſuch thing done to beaſts; and they that expect their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection might doe well to bury them more decently: that the world may ſee that they beleeve a reſurrection of beaſt.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, there is no example in Scripture, that any beaſt ever did riſe from death to life: but we have many examples of <hi>men and women received their dead raiſed to life againe, Heb.</hi> 11.35. and the man that was buried in the Sepulcher of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and touching his bones, he revived and ſtoode upon his feete, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 12.21. And in the New Teſtament, one newly dead, and another in the coffin, and another dead foure dayes and many came out of their graves at the death of Chriſt: then if we have ſo many examples of men that aroſe, and not one of beaſts: we muſt beleeve the one, and reject the other as an abominable errour.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, beaſts can neither dye the death of ſinne, nor ſuffer the death of eternall puniſhment: neither can they riſe to the ſtate of grace, nor to the ſtate of glory,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113584:11"/>which were a moſt miſerable and ſhamefull thing for any to affirme: therefore there is no reſurrection for beaſis.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, To riſe from death to life at the laſt day is called <hi>the reſurrection of the juſt and the unjuſt, Acts.</hi> 24.15. Now if they ſay that beaſts have done evill, they ſhall come forth to the reſurrection of damnation, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 9 25. or if ſome have done good, and ſome evill, then ſome of them ſhall be ſaved, and ſome damned: and then they muſt come before Chriſt the Judge on the Throne, to receive either the ſentence of abſolution, or condemnation: Theſe abominable errours are not fitting to be named amongſt Chriſtians, much leſſe to be embraced, and defended by any; and it would ſeeme incredible that any ſhould be ſo blinde as to harb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſuch errours where the light of the Goſpell comes: but onely we know at the downefall of Antichriſt. The divell will ſtir up all the old hereſies, that ever was, to uphold that tottering Babell.</p>
               <p>But to come againe to the argument, the covenant of workes was not made with beaſts, but with man onely: then it was not the beaſts but man onely that ſinned againſt that Covenant, of workes and man onely was puniſhed for the breach of it, and not the beaſts; although his puniſhments was not only upon his perſon, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his whole eſtate, and ſo accidentally the beaſts were puniſhed, but not as their puniſhment for their ſinne, but as mans puniſhment for his ſinne. Then if beaſts have neither ſinne nor puniſhment, from what ſhould they be redeemed? but they ſay, if all men were not redeemed, how ſhould they riſe again? I anſwer, Although all men are not redeemed, neither doe they all riſe by vertue of redemption: yet Chriſt by his power will raiſe thoſe that are not redeemed, to partake of that puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that is due to them for acting in that ſinne with their ſoules, when the whole man broke Covenant with the Eternall God. But they ſay, it is ſufficient to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the ſoule eternally, although the body riſe not. I anſwer, if they had kept that Covenant, the body ſhould have had the benefit of it to eternity: therefore becauſe it ſinned with the ſoule, it muſt ſuffer with it eternally. But they ſay the body riſeth without ſinne. I anſwer, yet if it did ſo, the ſoule being filthy and comming out of hell, will defile it, as a juſt requitall to the body which defiled the cleane ſoule as ſoone as it was infuſed into it: but I ſuppoſe the bodies of repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates ſhall not riſe without ſinne. But as the tree falls ſo it lies: there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance in the grave, <hi>but the ſame body and no other ſhall ariſe. Job.</hi> 19.26. <hi>For ſin ſhall lye downe with him in the duſt Job.</hi> 20.11. and having the guilt of ſinne upon it. As a Part of the curſe it ſhall be raiſed to partake with the ſoule in puniſhment: for the whole man ſinned, and the whole man ſhall be puniſhed eternally. But they ſay, As by the ſinne of one man, death came upon all men and beaſts, ſo by one man came the reſurrection of the dead: <hi>For in Adam all dye, ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.21, 22. Anſw. Beaſts were but the goods of men, it was man onely that ſinned, and was puniſhed: for all men being in <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned, and died for their owne ſinne: for it was theirs as ſoone as they were in him by nature; ſo alſo thoſe that are in Chriſt ſhall riſe againe to grace here, and to glory hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:113584:11"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Turne thee yet againe, and ſee greater abominations: They hold an Vniverſall Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if not both of men and beaſts, yet of all men: although they be already in hell torments.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>ELias will come and restore all things.</hi> I anſwer, <hi>Elias</hi> is already come, for it was <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt. See <hi>Math.</hi> 11.13.14. <hi>Luke.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Mark.</hi> 9 11, 12. But <hi>John</hi> cannot redeeme a ſoule from hell: but then they ſay, As all bare the image of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſo were caſt out of that Paradiſe, ſo all beare the image of the heavenly <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſhall come to his Paradiſe. But I ſay, the text ſaith not all: <hi>But as we have borne the image of the earthly, we ſhall beare the image of the heavenly: But no fleſh and bloud ſhall inherit the Kingdome of God.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.49, 50. But they ſay, though they belong in that boyling lake, it will be happy for them in the end: for they ſhall be there but till they have put off their mortall eſtate, and at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, theſe Captives ranſome ſhall be fully paide, and <hi>Origin</hi> was of their Judgement: but ſee here how they pleade for Purgatory, <hi>But thoſe in hell ſhall ſuffer the vengeance of eternall fire. Iude.</hi> 7. <hi>They ſhall depart from Chriſt into everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting fire. Math</hi> 25.41. <hi>where the fire is not quenched. Mark.</hi> 9.46. But they ſay, God reprobates none, but upon ſome fore-ſeene evill, nor elects any, but upon ſome fore-ſeene good: but here it ſeemes, they hold it poſſible to doe ſome good in hell, where they blaſpheme God for ever, and doe not repent, to give him glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>Revel.</hi> 16.9.11. but they ſay, thoſe that ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt ſhall be in danger of eternall fire, but not in it: but I ſay, <hi>They that blaſpheme againſt the Holy Ghoſt, ſhall neither be forgiven in this world, nor in the world to come. Math.</hi> 12.32. Then how ſhall they eſcape it? but they ſay, <hi>Abraham</hi> gives <hi>Dives</hi> in hell a loving title <hi>calling him Sonne. Luke.</hi> 16.25. therefore there is hope to come out. I anſwer, It was but a complement, yet he was the Sonne of God by creation, and yet not his Sonne by redemption from hell. But they ſay, Chriſt would not have preached to thoſe Spirits in priſon, if they ſhould for ever abide there. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Chriſt did not preach to them in hell, but to thoſe that were impriſoned by their ſinnes in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> while the Arke was preparing. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.19, 20. and by this argument, divels may be ſaved out of hell as well as they; but they ſay, there is hope that <hi>Iudas</hi> ſhall come out of hell, becauſe Chriſt ſeemes to be ſorry for his being there, ſaying, <hi>It had beene good if he had not beene borne. Math</hi> 26.24. I anſwer, It had beene well for <hi>Iudas</hi> himſelfe if he had not beene borne, becauſe of his eternall miſery. But his damnation addes no ſorrow to Chriſt. <hi>Neither mens righteouſneſſe nor his finne, nor his ſalvation nor damnation, neither profits God, nor takes any thing from him. Iob.</hi> 22.2, 3.35.6, 7, 8. but they ſay, although he deſerved to be tormented millions of yeares in hell, <hi>yet with Chriſt there is plenty of redemption<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pſal.</hi> 130. I anſwer, Chriſt hath merits ſufficient, but not efficient for reprobates</p>
               <p>But then if thoſe be not redeemed out of hell torments, yet they are confiden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that it is the truth, and nothing but the truth that Chriſt died for all, and ever man in the world. Their ſcriptures are thoſe, <hi>Chriſt was mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lower then the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> that by the grace of God he ſhould taſte death for every man, Heb.</hi> 2 9. <hi>And he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:113584:12"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:113584:12"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:113584:13"/>himſelf a ranſome for all,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 2.6. I Anſw. that neither of theſe places will prove that Chriſt died for all the world, or for every man in the world: for the word <hi>World</hi> is not in thoſe texts: <hi>And if any man ſhall adde unto theſe things, God ſhall adde unto him the plagues that are written in this booke, Revel.</hi> 22.18. Let us ſee what more proofes they have that Chriſt died for all, and every man in the world.</p>
               <p>Then they ſay, <hi>All we like ſheepe have gone aſtray, and we have tnrned every man to his owne way: and the Lord hath laide on him the iniquity of us all, Iſai.</hi> 53.6. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, this text is limited to us, and therefore is not to be taken for all, and every man in the world: but onely it was a comfort to thoſe to whom he ſpake, being either then converted or elſe in the uſe of the Ordinances which is the meanes of converſion and ſalvation: and therefore in the judgement of charity, we have gon aſtray, but the Lord hath laide on Chriſt <hi>the iniquities of us all;</hi> and yet he might be deceived, as well as <hi>Paul</hi> was in <hi>Demas.</hi> But then they ſay, <hi>The Angel brought glad tidings of great joy which ſhall be for all people, Luke</hi> 2.10. But here I hope, they will not ſay, that all and every man in the world ſhall be glad, and truely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in Chriſt: for then all and every man in the world ſhall be truely converted and ſaved, which themſelves deny; and beſides the word World is not in that text.</p>
               <p>But then they ſay, <hi>Chriſt taketh away the ſinnes of the world, Iohn</hi> 1.29. <hi>And Jeſus Chriſt is a propitiation for the ſinnes of the whole world,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.12. I anſwer, That world whoſe ſinnes Chriſt taketh away, and for whoſe perſons Chriſt is an Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, and a Propitiation, that world muſt needes be ſaved, as we ſhall ſee anon. But themſelves doe not holde that every man in the world ſhall be ſaved, and none of them ſhall periſh: then if they holde that ſome ſhall not be ſaved, but ſhall periſh, I hope thoſe that periſh are none of that world whoſe ſinnes Chriſt hath taken away, and for whoſe perſons he is an Advocate, and that world for whoſe ſinnes Chriſt is a Propitiation: then let us ſee the meaning of this word <hi>World,</hi> which in the Scriptures hath various ſignifications.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the Lord ſaith, <hi>the world is mine, Pſal.</hi> 50.12. this is to be underſtood, All the whole Fabricke of heaven and earth, and all the creatures in them; <hi>For the Lord made all things for himſelfe, Pro.</hi> 16.4. <hi>and he deſpoſeth the whole world Iob</hi> 34.13.</p>
               <p>Secondly, this word <hi>World</hi> is ſometimes underſtood this World here below in oppoſition to the world to come: for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I am no more in the world, but theſe are in the world; While I was with them in the world. Now I come to thee, theſe things I ſpeake in the world: I pray not that thou ſhouldest take them out of the world, Iohn</hi> 17.11.12, 13, 15. <hi>In this world you ſhall have an hundred fold, and in the world to come eternall life, Luke</hi> 18.28.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, this word World is ſometimes underſtoode the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> or all people beſides the <hi>Iewes: If th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fall of them be the riches of the world, Rom.</hi> 11.12.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Sometimes this word <hi>World</hi> is meant the whole race of mankinde: <hi>That every mouth may be ſtopped, and all the world may be guilty before God, Rom.</hi> 3.19.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Sometimes this word <hi>World</hi> is meant all the reprobates that ever were, or ever ſhall be, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I pray not for the world, Iohn</hi> 17.9.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, This word <hi>World</hi> is ſometimes taken for all the elect that ever were, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver ſhall be, <hi>Behold the Lamb of God that taketh away the ſins of the world, Iohn</hi> 1.29. <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.2.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:113584:13"/>
               <p>Seventhly, This word <hi>World</hi> ſometimes is meant the wicked of the world, who are in preſent being, <hi>The world hateth you, Iohn</hi> 15 19</p>
               <p>Eighthly, The World is ſometimes meant the godly in preſent being, <hi>Behold the world is gone after him, John</hi> 12.19.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, This word <hi>World</hi> is ſometimes taken for the elect in preſent being before converſion, <hi>Herein is love, not that we loved God, but that he loved us, and ſent his Sonne to be a Propitiation for our ſinnes,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.10. God that purpoaſed to love his people from all eternity, loves them actually, as his creatures, as ſoone as they have being in the world: ſo God loved <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> when they had ſinned as not to hate his owne worke in them, but loved it, and therefore ſent them a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>God ſo loved the world,</hi> thoſe in preſent, being yet not as his children, <hi>till he hath ſent to them his Sonne, and hath given them ſaith to receive him: then as many as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him, he gave power to become the Sonnes of God, to them that beleeve in his name, Iohn</hi> 1.12. Now let us trie whether Chriſt died for all theſe worlds; if not, let us ſee for which of theſe worlds he died.</p>
               <p>Firſt, if Chriſt died for the univerſall world, then he died for divels, and for An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels that never ſinned, and for the creatures in the whole world: yet I deny not but the Angels that never ſinned, and all mortall creatures have ſome benefit by his death, in reſpect of eſtabliſhment, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 49.8. but I utterly deny that Chriſt died to redeeme any creatures but mankinde only: <hi>He tooke not on him the nature of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, but the ſeede of Abraham to make reconciliation for the ſinnes of the people, Heb.</hi> 2.16, 17. <hi>To ſave his people from their ſinnes, Math.</hi> 1.21. neither can it be underſtood that Chriſt died for the world of <hi>Gentiles</hi> onely: <hi>For he was ſent to the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of Iſrael, Math.</hi> 14.24. and the Angels told the <hi>Jewes,</hi> ſaying, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you is borne this day a Saviour, which is Chriſt the Lord, Luke</hi> 2.10. And for the world of the elect, I know none that makes queſtion of it, whether called or uncalled to the eſtate of grace: yet in Gods due time they ſhall be ſure to finde the benefit of it; So then here lies our controverſie, they affirme that Chriſt died for all the wicked and reprobats in the world: but I affirme the contrary upon theſe grounds.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Chriſt died for the elect onely: for ſaith <hi>Paul, From the beginning God hath choſen you to ſalvation through ſanctification of the ſpirit and beleefe of the truth,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. He ſaith, <hi>I have choſen and ordained you that you ſhould goe and bring forth fruite, Iohn</hi> 15.16. <hi>Chriſt was ordained for you who doe beleeve in God, ſeeing you have purified your ſoules in obeying the truth.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20 21. <hi>As many as were ordained to eternall life beleeved, Acts</hi> 13.48. that is called <hi>the faith of Gods elect, Tit.</hi> 1 1. <hi>Thoſe who are prediſtinated, he calleth, juſtifieth and glorifieth, Rom.</hi> 8.30. But <hi>Heaven is not appointed for all, it ſhall be given to them for whom it was prepared, Math.</hi> 20.23. <hi>Some ſtumble at the word, being diſobedient whereunto they were appointed,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 2 8. <hi>Some of old were ordained to this condemnation, Jude</hi> 4. <hi>And ſome are called to inherit a Kingdome prepared for them, and ſome are charged to depart into everlaſting fire pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them. Math.</hi> 25.34 41. <hi>Some are veſſels of mercy prepared for glory, and ſome are veſſels of wrath fitted for deſtruction, Rom.</hi> 9.22.23. <hi>Thoſe unnaturall brute beaſts were made to be deſtroyed,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12. Then are ſome ordained to ſalvation, and others to damnation, and ſome ordained to the meanes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:113584:14"/>and not others: and for ſome heaven is prepared, and for others hell is prepared; then ſure Chriſt did not dye for all, and every man in the world: and that world whoſe ſinne Chriſt taketh away, and is a Propitiation, and for whoſe perſons he is an Advocate, is onely the elect, which may be called a world for multitude, <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.19. <hi>Revel.</hi> 19.6. But then they ſcornfully anſwer, ſaying, they will reade world alwayes where they finde the word, elect; and elect alwayes where they finde the word <hi>World;</hi> then thus ſaith Chriſt <hi>I pray for them, I pray not for the elect, but for thoſe that thou haſt given me out of the elect, and I am no more in the elect, Iohn</hi> 17.9.11. <hi>And this is condemnation, that light is come into the elect, Iohn</hi> 3.19. Thus changing the ſignification of the word <hi>World,</hi> they bring in this damnable conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in ſcornfull deriſion of the truth of God. But they ſay, if Chriſt died for none but the elect, then unbeleefe is no ſinne, and ſome would ſin in beleeving Chriſt hath died for them, when it is not ſo. I anſwer, God gave man faith at the firſt to beleeve that it he had done as he commanded, he ſhould have lived for ever, and although man hath loſt this grace of faith, yet God hath not loſt his power to command man to uſe this faith. Man is to beleeve in Chriſt; and if he doe not, he ſinnes againſt the Goſpell: no man can ſinne in beleeving that Chriſt hath died for his ſin, when it is not ſo, for if he truly beleeve he ſhall be ſaved and then it is ſo.</p>
               <p>Secondly Chriſt did not die for all, and every man in the world; for he died for none but thoſe which his Father gave him; <hi>He came not to doe his owne will, but the will of his Father that ſent him: He muſt doe his Fathers buſineſſe, Luke</hi> 2.49. <hi>And he muſt finiſh the worke he gave him to doe, Iohn</hi> 17 4. <hi>But it is the Fathers will that all which he gave him that he ſhould loſe none, Iohn</hi> 6.39. but all was not given to Chriſt; <hi>not the world, but thoſe that thou haſt given me, Iohn</hi> 17.6. and God gave him no reprobates: for Chriſt gave his eternall life, <hi>to all that his Father gave him, verſe</hi> 2. <hi>And the Father commanded him to lay downe his life for thoſe that he gave him, Iohn</hi> 10.17.18. But if Chriſt had died for more then his Father gave him, then it ſeems Chriſt would have more then was agreed by the Father to give him, but this would faſten ſinne upon Chriſt in not being content, but to will have more then his Covenant: then Chriſt died not for all, and every man in the world; but then they will grant that Chriſt died for no more then his Father gave him: for ſay they <hi>All things are delivered unto him of his Father, Math.</hi> 11.27. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2 7.8. I anſwer, It is true divels and reprobates are under his Regall power to rule them with a rodde of iron; but none are under his Scepter of grace and glory but his elect: therefore he died for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Chriſt died not for all and every man in the world, for <hi>He was the good ſhepheard, who gave his life for the ſheepe, Iohn</hi> 10 11.15. but all are not the ſheepe of Chriſt, neither by election nor calling: <hi>For at the day of Judgement, Chriſt will divide the ſhe perfrom the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tes, and ſar to the ſheepe, Come ye bleſſed, and to the goats Goe ye curſed, Math.</hi> 25.33.41. then Chriſt did not die for all and every man in the world: but they will grant this ſaying, Chriſt died for all, and therefore for his ſheepe: but I ſay againe that they muſt be ſheepe either in election that ſhall be brought into this folde. <hi>Iohn</hi> 10 16. or elſe they are already in the folde by calling; but this will not prove that he died for the goates and dogges that ſhall <gap reason="missing" extent="4 pages">
                     <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:113584:14"/>
               <p>Fourthly, Chriſt dyed onely for them that he knows, <hi>The Lord knows who are his,</hi> 2 <hi>Tom.</hi> 2.19. And <hi>Chriſt knows his ſheep,</hi> John 10.27. and as the Father hath his book, wherein the names of all his are written, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.20. <hi>So the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> hath his book of life,</hi> Revel. 13.8. But ſome at the laſt day will neither be found written in the book of life, nor in the Lambs book, therefore he will profeſſe unto them that he never knew them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.21, 22. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.17. So that if Chriſt knows his ſheep for which he died, and yet at the day of judgement there ſhall be ſome that he never knew, then Chriſt did not die for all and every man in the world.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Chriſt dyed for no more then he prayed for, and now makes interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion but ſayth he, <hi>I pray not for the world, John</hi> 17.9. and not to make interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the Saints, according to the will of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.27. He makes interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for all that come unto God by him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. And, ſayth he, <hi>I pray not for theſe alone, but for them alſo that ſhall beleeve through the Word,</hi> John 17.2. Thus Chriſt prayed for all the elect that ſhall come unto God by him, and that ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him, but ſome he would not pray for, but ſayth, <hi>I pray not for the world, Joh.</hi> 17.9. for then if Chriſt would not vouchſafe to pray for all, and every man in the world, ſhall we thinke that he would die and ſpill his bloud for all: But ſay they, all were given to Chriſt, and if he prayes for all thoſe that were given to him, then he prayes for all. I anſwer, all reprobates are given to his power, to be ruled by his rod of iron; theſe are under his regall government, that they ſhall not doe what they liſt, he hath a bridle for their lips, and a hook in their noſe, theſe hee rules with rigour, and becauſe they will not doe his will they ſhall ſuffer this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure: But the other he rules with ſanctifying and ſaving grace, but to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee will neither give grace not glory, therefore he neither prayed nor dyed for them.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, Thoſe for whom Chriſt dyed, it was to redeem them from all iniquity, <hi>Titus</hi> 2.14. <hi>The precious bloud of Chriſt redeemed us from our vain converſation,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet,</hi> 1.18, 19. <hi>The bloud of Chriſt ſhall purge your conſciences from dead works, to ſerve the living God,</hi> Heb. 9.14. <hi>He waſhed us from our ſins in his bloud.</hi> Rev. 1.5. <hi>But ſome ſhall never have their ſins purged,</hi> Ezek. 24.13. Some their ſins ſhall never be forgiven in this world nor in the world to come. <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.31. Then if Chriſt dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to redeem from ſin, and by his death to reconcile ſome to God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10. and yet ſome ſhall never be forgiven, neither ſin purged, then Chriſt did not die for all and every man in the world.</p>
               <p>But they ſay, Chriſt takes away the ſins of the whole world, yet they believe that he juſtifies none from their ſins, till they behold and believe it, <hi>John</hi> 1.29.</p>
               <p>I Anſwer, If none be juſtified till they believe that Chriſt takes away the ſins of all and every man in the world, then they ſhall never be juſtified, for as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſome ſhall never be forgiven nor their ſins purged, then if all ſin ſhall he to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away by Chriſt, and yet the Father will not juſtifie them, this were to ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113584:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:113584:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:113584:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:113584:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:113584:17"/>God to bee unjuſt. Again, ſhall not I be ſaved unleſſe I make CHRIST a lyer? Doth hee ſay ſome ſhall never bee forgiven, and cannot I bee juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied unleſſe I believe that he taketh away the ſins of every man in the world.</p>
               <p>Again, If Chriſt takes away the ſins of every man in the world, I would know what elſe can hinder their juſtification or ſalvation? Is not God true in his word to CHRIST, to ſave them that hee hath freed from ſinne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, For this is the Fathers will, ſayth Chriſt, <hi>That all which hee hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven mee, I ſhould loſe nothing, but that I ſhould raiſe it up at the laſt day, John</hi> 6.39. Then doth the Father want power to keepe thoſe that Chriſt hath redeemed? No, <hi>My Father is greater then all, and no man is able to pluck them out of my Fathers hand,</hi> John 10.29. Then did Chriſt loſe them again? no, hee ſaith, <hi>All thoſe that thou haſt given me, I have loſt none but the ſonne of perdition,</hi> who was onely given to him by office but not by grace and favour: then what is the fault, are their ſins forgiven and taken away by Chriſt, and yet they will not bee ſaved, this cannot be, for ſayth the Father to the Sonne, <hi>Thy people ſhall bee willing in the day of thy power, Pſal.</hi> 110.3. Then let Popiſh Arminians bee aſhamed to ſay, CHRIST taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſinnes of every man in the World, and yet the greateſt part of it damned: <hi>For nothing but ſinne ſeparates between us and our God: Eſay</hi> 50.2.</p>
               <p>Then they ſay, it is not the death of Chriſt that makes any difference of men, <hi>For he gave his life a ranſom for all,</hi> and would have all ſaved, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.1, 2. And it is predeſtination and faith that makes the difference.</p>
               <p>I Anſwer, It is true, It was decreed that CHRIST ſhould die for the elect, and their faith believes that hee hath done it, and ſo they are juſtified, and ſhall be ſaved: But then they ſay, there bee two elections, one generall for all men.</p>
               <p>But the other is not decreed till men believe, and is particular for belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers: For ſay they, if God ſhould make ſome men which hee doth not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to be ſaved, he would be the poſitive cauſe of ſin in them, and then for that ſin he cauſed to damne them which would be miſerable.</p>
               <p>Truly I anſwer, God is not the poſitive cauſe of ſin in any, hee never infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſinne into them, hee made man righteous, yet mutable, and hee was not bonnd to ſupport him, therefore hee fell, yet God did not make man to damne him, nor deſires hee the deſtruction of any creature, but hee deſires the glory of his juſtice, and better all creatures ſhould periſh then hee ſhould loſe the glory of his juſtice; as in our own caſe, better the creatures die then wee ſhould want food, yet wee doe not kill them, as deſiring their deſtruction, but to ſatisfie our hunger, ſo doth the Lord for the glory of his Juſtice.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:113584:17"/>
               <p>But they ſay, God doth not decree to damne them, till hee hath tryed and found that they will not be ſaved: but I ſay again, God never decreed to damne any, but onely he decreed to glorifie his juſtice, and for that he need not ſtay to ſee what man will doe, <hi>can any deliver out of his hand, if he worke, who can let it?</hi> Eſay 43.13.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, Thoſe for whom Chriſt dyed, ſhall be juſtified and ſaved, for <hi>The free gift came upon all, to juſtification of life, Rom.</hi> 5.18. and <hi>Whom he juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhall be glorified, Rom.</hi> 8.30.33. Who ſhall condemn, if Chriſt hath dyed for them, <hi>ver.</hi> 34. <hi>The ranſommed of the Lord ſhall come to Sion with everlaſting joy,</hi> Eſay 35.10. But ſome ſhall neither be juſtified nor glorified, but condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and puniſhed everlaſtingly, therefore they are none of thoſe that Chriſt dyed for, nor none of thoſe ranſomed of the Lord, then Chriſt did not die for all, and every man in the world.</p>
               <p>But they ſay the death of Chriſt, for all and every man in the world, is the foundation of juſtifying faith.</p>
               <p>I Anſwer, That cannot be, but this is rather a ground of it, that Chriſt hath not dyed for all but for ſome of mankind, and then with a ſpeciall faith to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that he hath dyed for me in particular, and this faith inſtrumentally juſtifies us, but when we believe with a generall faith, that Chriſt dyed for all men, this cuts off a ſpeciall faith, for our ſelves are one of the whole world, and ſo wee ſhall apply it to our ſelves no more then to any reprobates.</p>
               <p>Then they ſay, If all ſhall be ſaved for whom Chriſt dyed, then none of them could periſh, but ſome ſhall periſh for whom Chriſt dyed, and are damned that he bought, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.11. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. I anſwer, It was but in the judgement of charity that Chriſt dyed or bought them, but they ſay, <hi>Chriſt came not to judge the world, but to ſave the world, Iohn</hi> 12.47, 48. Therefore he dyed for all, I Anſwer, while Chriſt is mediator, he is come to ſave the world, and not to judge them that believe not, but at the laſt day his words ſhall judge them and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them. So then his firſt comming is to ſave the world, not the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall world, but the multitude of the elect, which may well be called a world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo great a multitude, <hi>Revel.</hi> 19. And as the Iews ſaid, <hi>The world is gone after him,</hi> Iohn 12.19. Then they ſay, God ſo loved the world, that hee gave them his onely begotten Son, and yet none are ſaved but they that believe in him, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.16. Hence, ſay they, Chriſt is given to all, and yet faith makes the difference, and <hi>hath the promiſe of eternall life,</hi> and not the other, although Chriſt dyed for them, and Gods love to all, and yet not all ſaved: But if God love them, I would know what could hinder their ſalvation, ſhall Gods beloved ones periſh, ſo then their concluſion is this, not he whom God loves ſhall be ſaved, but he that will of himſelfe believe, ſhall have eternall life, but <hi>it is not in him that willeth, nor in him that runneth but in God that ſheweth mercie,</hi> for his will ſhall ſtand, and hee will doe all his pleaſure.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:113584:18"/>
               <p>Then they ſay, Chriſt came to his own, <hi>and his own received him not, Iohn.</hi> 1.12. but that is not his fault, for he comes unto them, but it is their own fault, for they will not receive him, ſo they conclude they are his by purchaſe, and yet they will not be ſaved, I anſwer, they were his own viſible Church by a Nationall Covenant, having his Ordinances, and diſtinguiſhed from other Nations by circumciſion, and not by any true work of grace in their heart, and ſo others might goe to heaven, when thoſe children of the Kingdom are thruſt out, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.12. Or if it be ſpoken of any of the elect that were his own, and yet would not receive him, it was but onely at that preſent, yet after they had crucified him at <hi>Peters</hi> Sermon they received him, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.41.</p>
               <p>Then they ſay, put the caſe that Chriſt taketh away the ſins of the world, and this world is the elect, then it muſt needs follow that ſome of the elect ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, but what a damnable inference is this? Chriſt taketh away the ſins of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, therefore ſome of the elect muſt needs periſh. I anſwer, It is true, if wee ſhould maintain as they doe, that God hath elected everyman in the world, which would be no election to take all, but the elect is a certain number choſen of God, and given to Chriſt, whoſe ſins he hath taken away, or at leaſt is taking them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and when that work is finiſhed they ſhall be glorified, and that world, meaning the multitude of the elect that Chriſt came to ſave, ſhall certainly be ſaved, <hi>For the Lord hath laid help upon one that is mighty, Pſal.</hi> 89.19. <hi>He is migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſave, Eſay</hi> 63.1. <hi>And he hath finiſhed the work his Father gave him to doe, Iohn</hi> 17.4. and ſtill he is his Son, <hi>in whom he is well pleaſed,</hi> then how ſhall they miſcarry, when Chriſt takes away their ſins, to this they have a bundle of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments together, as if they would prove that Chriſt dyed for all and every man in the world, although the greateſt part be not ſaved but damned.</p>
               <p n="1">1 They ſay, Chriſt dyed for all thoſe that are damned, that he might get the victory over ſin, death, hell, and the Devill, by his own death and triumph over all, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Iob</hi> 2.9. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.19, 20, 21, 22, 23. <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.10.</p>
               <p>I Anſwer, Is it a ſigne of victory, over hell, death, ſin, and Satan, when they ſhall take from Chriſt thoſe that he hath bought with his heart bloud, if Chriſt hath paid for them, ſhall death and hell, ſin and Satan, take them out of his hand, when as he ſayth, <hi>no man ſhall pluck them out of his hand, and his Father is greater then all, and no man ſhall pluck them out of his Fathers hand,</hi> Joh. 10.28, 29. then ſhall the devill and ſin doe it to get victory to your Saviour, but it ſeems by this, that the Devill is your Saviour and not Chriſt, for if Chriſt have the keyes of hell, then none ſhall periſh that he hath bought, and this is his victory, that he will ſave them in ſpight of all his enemies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.2. But they ſay, if all the Sins in the world had not been laid on Chriſt, but the ſins of the elect onely, then he had not gotten the victory over all ſin, but over ſome ſin. I anſwer, all ſorts of ſins are in his people which he hath overcome, that it dies daily in them, and for the ſins of reprobates, they ſhall be reſtrained by him, and at leſt, all things
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113584:18"/>that offend, ſhall be taken out of his Kingdom, and caſt into the furnace of ſin, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.41, 42. <hi>Both reprobates and their ſins ſhall be caſt into hell fire,</hi> and the Saints ſhall inherit all things, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.7.</p>
               <p>Their ſecond reaſon why Chriſt dyed for all, and yet all not ſaved, is this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would have nothing preached to man but what is true, but if Chriſt dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not for all men, and yet the Goſpel preached to all, and requires all to believe, then ſome men are required to believe that which is not true. I anſwer, it is not ſin in God, to command man to believe in Chriſt, although he knows they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, becauſe he made them able at the firſt to doe it, if he had then required it, and if man by ſin hath now diſabled himſelfe, yet God is not to be blamed for requiring that which he made them able to do at the firſt, no more then a man is that hath two debtors, and both diſable to pay him, the one he freely forgives, and of the other he requires the debt; nor doth he require them to believe that which is not true, when the Goſpel is preached unto them, but if they can truly believe they ſhall be ſaved, and preaching the Goſpel is the inſtrumentall means to work faith in men <hi>that they may believe, Rom.</hi> 10.1. and then, <hi>He that beleeveth ſhall be ſaved, Mar.</hi> 16.16. Again, the Lord ſomtimes ſends his Goſpel to try if men will repent and believe, and if we doe not repent and believe; it makes us guilty of a great ſin in not doing of it, when he requiers it of us, and to ſay God requires ſome to believe that which is not true, is a ſin to judge of the ſecret will of God before that he hath revealed it unto them.</p>
               <p>Their third reaſon, why Chriſt dyed for all and yet all not ſaved, they ſay is, to leave man without excuſe, for man cannot ſay that Chriſt hath not dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for him, and the Goſpel was preached to every creature to leave many without excuſe. I Anſwer, Will God give the greateſt gift that ever hee gave to man as well to reprobates, as to the elect, to leave them without excuſe? Would not a leſſe gift then Chriſt himſelfe bee ſufficient to leave them without excuſe? But then they would confirme this from theſe words of <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaying, <hi>The free gift came upon all men, unto juſtification of life, Rom.</hi> 5.18. Hence they would gather that Chriſt hath dyed for all men, For by him all are juſtified, and have life by Chriſt, and yet many of them ſhall bee damned. O helliſh inference, all this is to leave them without excuſe, but the truth is this, as by the offence of <hi>Adam</hi> judgement came upon all men that were in him by nature, even ſo ſayth this Text, by one Chriſt, the free gift of righteouſneſſe, came upon all the elect, when they are in him by grace, unto juſtification of life, for as none is guilty of the firſt <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, till they are in him by nature, ſo, nor is righteouſneſſe by Chriſt, till they are in him by grace, and not many ages paſt they ſaid, although Chriſt taketh away the ſins of all the world, yet none are juſtified from the ſin, till they by faith behold it, but here they are not aſhamed to ſay that the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113584:19"/>God ſhould pronounce all to be juſt, having given them Chriſt to die for their ſins, and the life of grace to believe it, and after all this that God ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne theſe juſtified perſons: What miſerable blaſphemy is this? <hi>Shall not the Judge of all the earth doe right? Gen.</hi> 18.25. <hi>Is God unrighteous that taketh vengeance, how then ſhall he judge the world? Rom.</hi> 3.5, 6. Then doe not harbour ſuch blaſphemous thoughts of God, for whom he juſtified, them he alſo glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>It is God that juſtifieth, who ſhall condemn? It is Chriſt that dyed, Rom.</hi> 8.30, 33, 34.</p>
               <p>The fourth reaſon, Why Chriſt dyed for all, and yet not all ſaved, is this, they ſay Chriſt dyed for <hi>Adam</hi> and all his poſterity, becauſe the elect ſhould proceed out of his loynes. I Anſwer, as they are fleſh and bloud they are the children of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſo in him under ſin and condemnation, but as they are new borne they proceed from the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> which is Chriſt, <hi>Hee ſhall ſee his ſeed, and he ſhall ſee the travell of his ſoule, and be ſatisfied, Eſay</hi> 53.10, 11. God the Father by Covenant gave them to Chriſt from all Eternity, therfore ſayth he, <hi>Behold, I and the children which thou haſt given me, Eſay</hi> 8.18. But will it follow, that all muſt be elected becauſe all ſinned, and muſt all be given to Chriſt becauſe they are deſcended of <hi>Adam,</hi> or muſt Chriſt die for all becauſe all came of <hi>Adam?</hi> By this reaſon, what is done to any, is done to all, if any be ſaved, all are ſaved, if any be damned all are damned, becauſe wee have all our nature from one man, but cannot God beſtow his gift on whom hee will? muſt all have a like, becauſe all are alike deſcended? I hope when <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> had condemned all, it was Gods free grace to pardon any, and as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as he pleaſeth.</p>
               <p>The fifth reaſon why Chriſt dyed for all, and yet all not ſaved, is, becauſe by Chriſt all ſhall riſe again at the laſt day, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.21, 22. Hee is called the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, <hi>John</hi> 11, 25. For by the ſin of <hi>Adam</hi> all die, and ſo loſt their bodies, ſo by Chriſt ſhall all riſe again, ſome to the reſurrection of ſalvatian, and ſome to the reſurrection of damnation, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.29. Then ſay they, becauſe Chriſt raiſeth all, therefore he dyed for all. I Anſwer, although it is by Chriſt all reprobates are raiſed, that is, by his power, thoſe veſſels of wrath that are fitted for deſtruction may be filled with it, and becauſe the body of <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned as well as the ſoule, againſt an infinite God, therefore the bodies of reprobates ſhould be puniſhed with their ſouls eternally, and becauſe Chriſt will ſend his Angels to gather up the bodies of reprobates, to bring them to their ſoules to bee tormented eternally: Is this a good argument that Chriſt hath dyed for them, and bought thoſe ſoules and bodies, this ſhews plainly they are goats, and none of the ſheep that the good ſheepherd dyed for, they are dogs and ſhall bee without, when as his ſheep ſhall never periſh, <hi>but ſhall have eternall life. John</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, They ſay Chriſt dyed for all, and yet not all ſaved, becauſe the Father
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113584:19"/>gave him all. I anſwer, Thoſe that are given in to his wrath to be ruled with a rod of iron, to ſay he dyed for all ſuch, you had as good ſay that hee died for devills, being ſo given on to his regall power, that they ſhall not doe what they liſt, but then they ſay he died for all, to purchaſe to himſelfe a Church: But can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not a man purchaſe a Lordſhip unleſſe he lay down money, and bargain for the whole World, and when he hath purchaſed all the World, and then ſtand to their courteſie, whether any will bee ſaved or not, what miſerable arguing is this?</p>
               <p>Seventhly, They ſay, Chriſt dyed for all, and yet all not ſaved, becauſe <hi>His Father made him Iudge of all,</hi> John 5.27, 28, 29. I anſwer as before, by this Argument he dyed for Devills and Angels that never ſinned, for he is the judge of all, but if Chriſt ſhall ſlay thoſe that will not have him to rule over them, and caſt unprofitable ſervants into utter darkneſſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.22, 27. and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vengeance on theſe that obey not the Goſpel, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7, 8, 9. Is this ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to prove that Chriſt hath bought them with his heart bloud when hee ſhall thus condemne nhem, let all wiſe men judge. But then they ſay, if Chriſt ſhould condemne theſe that he dyed not for, in that he would be unjuſt. I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer as before, If this were ſo, then Chriſt were unjuſt to condemne the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills, or elſe they muſt prove that Chriſt dyed for Devills, but men and Angels were all condemned for their ſin againſt the Covenant of works, and hee was not bound to ſend men a Saviour to redeem them, and to eſtabliſh thoſe Angels that did not ſin. This may ſuffice to prove that Chriſt did not die for all and every man in the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> 
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>They hold it unlawlull to uſe that Prayer of Chriſt, <hi>Matthew 6.9.</hi> at a Prayer both by the godly and ungodly.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THey ſay the godly muſt not uſe this Prayer of Chriſt, becauſe the fift petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, <hi>forgive us our trespaſſes,</hi> when as they are forgiven already, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought not to pray for pardon of ſin, being pardoned already. I Anſwer, <hi>David</hi> a man after Gods own heart, when <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet told him that the Lord had put away his ſin, yet he prayed the Lord to deliver him from bloud guiltineſſe, 2 <hi>Sam,</hi> 12.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.14. and in his old age he prayed the Lord not to remember the ſins of his youth, and to pardon his iniquity, for it is great <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.7, 11. And although the Lord will cleanſe the houſe of Iſrael from all their uncleanneſſe, yet for this he will be enquired of by them <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25, 26, 29, 97. <hi>And they muſt take up words and ſay, take away all our iniquity, Hoſ.</hi> 14.2. and the Apoſtles by Chriſt were taught daily to ſay <hi>forgive us our ſins,</hi> becauſe we
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113584:20"/>ſin daily, and our aſſurance is but for the time preſent, and who knows how ſoone he may loſe it: and ſay with <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah, I am cut off, Pſal.</hi> 31.22. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.54. and with <hi>Iob,</hi> Though thou holdeſt me for thine enemy, and ſetteſt me as a mark for thine arrow, <hi>Iob</hi> 7.20.13, 24. But they ſay, if any man lack aſſurance of Gods favour, let him pray for it, rather then for pardon of ſin, being done al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, I anſwer aſſurance of Gods favour is employed in that prayer for pardon of ſin, for it is ſin onely that ſeparates betweene us and our God, <hi>Eſay</hi> 59 2. and we ſhould more deſire the pardon of ſin being an offence to God then our own com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort that comes by that pardon: again, the way to get aſſurance and to keepe it, is by praying for the forgiveneſſe of ſins for ſuppoſe, we have at the preſent our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable aſſurance, that all our ſins paſt are forgiven, yet we ſin continually, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very new ſin is as a cloud betweene God and us, and darkens our aſſurance of it, now by this prayer we diſperſe and diſpell theſe clouds which would ſoon deprive us of all our comfortable aſſurance of Gods favour: therefore <hi>David</hi> prays to be <hi>clenſed from all his ſecret ſins,</hi> although unknown, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.12. for all ſinnes will cauſe the Lord to hide his face from us more or leſſe, <hi>Eſay</hi> 54.2. but they ſay Chriſt taught his Diſciples to pray for pardon of ſin before hee ſuffered, becauſe hee had then appeaſed the wrath of his Father, yet afterward hee required no ſuch thing, but if Chriſt had not ſatisfied the wrath of God before he came in the fleſh, and ſuffered in it then, I would know what became of all the Patriarks and Prophets that died before, but I have often ſaid, that God made a Covenant with Chriſt from all Eternity, to give him all the Elect as they fall in the ſeverall ages of the World upon condition, that he ſhould give his life a ranſome for them, and ſo the Father ſet him a day, and truſted the Son for the payment of it, and gave him all the elect, according to their Covenant that fell in thoſe ages, before the day of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the purchaſe, and then in the fulneſſe of time he paid for the purchaſe, and now the Son truſts the Father, to give him all the Elect that fall in thoſe ages ſince the purchaſe was paid: ſo then the death of Chriſt was vertuall to ſave thoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his comming, as well as thoſe after, for God was in Chriſt, reconciling the World or multitude of the Elect in every age of the World from the firſt to the laſt, to give them to Chriſt, and ſo by vertue of the Covenant, he was ſlaine from the foundation of the World, <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.8. Therefore it is ſaid by <hi>Iſaiah, unto us a child is born, Eſay</hi> 6.9. <hi>And Abraham ſaw his day and was glad,</hi> Joh. 8.58. And Chriſt was as pleaſing to his Father before he came in the fleſh as after, for, ſayth he, I was ſet up from everlaſting, then I was by him as one brought up with him, and I was daily his delight, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.23, 30. Therefore if Chriſt ſay in <hi>Jobs</hi> time, <hi>I have found a ranſome, then he will deliver his ſoule from going into the pit, and his life ſhall ſee the light, Iob</hi> 33.24, 28. ſo then in every age, when the Father gave any to Chriſt, his death did vertually ſatisfie for them, they being in Chriſt by faith, with whom the Covenant was made, but they ſay before Chriſt ſuffered all power to forgive ſins was in the Father, and afterward given to him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113584:20"/>And then and not before, <hi>he got the keyes of hell and death, Revel.</hi> 1.18. I Anſwer, Chriſt had power to forgive ſin before he ſuffered, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.5, 6. for he was King of his Church, ever ſince that promiſe was made to <hi>Adam, Gen.</hi> 3.15. and had the keyes of hell and death ever ſince, although he never made it known to the world till then, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.25. and if that covenant had not been made before, the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of works was broken by <hi>Adam,</hi> all creatures had periſhed eternally, but they ſay, although Chriſt taught remiſſion of ſins after his death, yet then he did not teach to pray for pardon of ſinne. I Anſwer, that prayer which he had taught before was to remain to the worlds end, for ſayth he, <hi>When you pray ſay, forgive us our ſins,</hi> and to denie this were to renounce all thoſe truths taught by him before his death, and to confine our ſelves onely to what hee taught afterwards. Again, then the Doctrine of reſurrection was moſt in queſtion to be reſolved on, therefore hee laboured to ſtrengthen the faith in that Doctrine onely, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.37, 39. <hi>John</hi> 20.27. and this doctrine of the reſurrection being confirmed, all other doctrines taught before were confirmed alſo. But they ſay, the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law may as well continue now as that prayer of Chriſt, for hee did as well then command them to goe and offer ſacrifice, as <hi>Moſes</hi> had commanded, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.4. I Anſwer, although the ſacrifices of beaſts did end at the death of CHRIST, yet the ſacrifices of prayer and praiſe was not then to end, for praiſe and thankſgiving muſt be continually in heaven, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.15. and that of thoſe Lepers was ſuch a ſacrifice, nine of them went not at all, and the tenth returned to CHRIST and gave him thanks, and it was approved of him as ſufficient, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.16, 18. ſo then, whether they were brought to Chriſt by the helpe of a ſacrifice or immediately, it was not much ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall, ſo that they came to him then, although the ſinne offering of beaſts be ceaſed, by the Sacrifice of CHRIST once for all, yet the ſacrifice of prayer for pardon of ſin may ſtill bee a ſweet incenſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 141.1. but they ſay, When Chriſt taught them thus to pray, the Law was in its full ſtrength, but now Chriſt hath put an end to the Law, which is the ſtrength of ſin. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.56. And the Law being ended, ſin alſo is ended, and needs no prayer for the pardon of it. I Anſwer, The morall Law is eternally ſetled in heaven, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.89, 103.20. and ſin remains in hell, for they ſhall blaſpheme God in their torments and cannot repent, <hi>Revel.</hi> 16.9, 11. and if ſinne ſhould ceaſe, the fire would goe out, for <hi>It is ſin and the wrath of God, that is like ariver of brimſtone to it, Eſay</hi> 30, 33. ſo then as in heaven is neither ſin nor miſery to the elect, but in hell is both the reprobate, and in this world all things are alike to all, <hi>Eccleſ</hi> 9, 1, 2, the Soints and reprobates have both ſin and miſerie, although in a different man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, for it reigns in the one, and is dying in the other, but he is a lyer that ſaith he hath no ſin, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.8. <hi>For no man liveth and ſinneth not,</hi> 1 <hi>King</hi> 8.48. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.20. Then feeing as the Saints have ſin, they muſt pray for the parden of it as the beſt means in the world to ſubdue it, then the godly may ſay this prayer.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:113584:21"/>
               <p>But then they ſay the ungodly may not ſay this Prayer of Chriſt as a Prayer, becauſe they cannot call God Father. I Anſwer, although they bee none of his children by grace and adoption yet they are his children by creation, thus <hi>Adam</hi> was the Son of God, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.38. and ſo God is the Father of all things, <hi>Job</hi> 38.28. and if carnall men doe pray, they may obtain ſome temporall things, as well as <hi>Ahab</hi> did by faſting, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.29. ſo God hears all mortall creatures, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.21.145.15.147 9. Then they ſay carnall men ought not to ſay the firſt petition <hi>praiſed be thy name,</hi> for they cannot doe it from the heart. I Anſwer, the beſt of us all when we pray, if Chriſt did not put the incenſe of his merits a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, could not be pleaſing unto him, <hi>Revel.</hi> 9.3. and if none ſhould praiſe the Lord, but thoſe that doe it with their whole heart, God would have very little praiſe in this world, when as every creature that hath breath, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to praiſe the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 150.6. Then they ſay, none can give God thanks, but they that have received ſomthing of him, but this I grant, for what creature in heaven, earth, or ſea, that hath received nothing from God? if there be none ſuch, but all have received of him ſomthing, then let all praiſe him. But they ſay, for carnall men to pray, <hi>Thy Kingdom come, thy will be done, on earth as it is in heaven,</hi> were to pray for their deſtruction, but how can that be, when they pray that the will of Chriſt were done hy man on earth, as Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels doe it in heaven, both chearfully and conſtantly in ſalvation, rather then by ſuffering his will upon them in hell torments for ever. Then they ſay that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall men may not ſay. <hi>Give us this day our daily bread,</hi> for that is to be underſtood, The word of God which the Saints have had, and ſtill deſire, but how can this be? muſt we aske for ſo much of the word as may onely ſuffice for a day? and doth the word of God conſume in the uſing of it, when, <hi>not one jot of it ſhall fail, Mat.</hi> 5. It was the loafes that Chriſt ſaid was meate that periſheth, <hi>John</hi> 6.26, 27. Again, if Chriſt in this petition did not teach us to pray for temporall things then how could his prayer be perfect, and why would hee give thanks for meate that periſheth, if he would not pray for a bleſſing upon it: Then they ſay, here is to be underſtood that Chriſt taught them to pray for his ſpirit, but I ſay again, how much of his ſpirit will ſuffice for a day, and I hope they will not ſo blaſpheme the eternall ſpirit of God, as to ſay it conſumes in the uſing of it, no, <hi>It is a well of living water, ſpringing up unto eternall life, John</hi> 4 14. then this, petition being for carnall things and not the ſpirit of God, carnall men may pray for them and obtain them. Then they ſay, if carnall men ſhould ſay forgive us as we forgive them that treſpas againſt us, in this they would ſeale up their own damnation, becauſe they will not forgive others, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.29, 30. But what of this, ſhall they eſcape damnation by not ſaying of it? and if they cannot, they had as good ſay it to obtain ſome temporall things, as to be both miſerable in not ſaying of it, both here, and alſo hereafter, and beſides the uſing well of theſe gifts in ſeeking them by prayer, and giving God thanks for them, is Gods way
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113584:21"/>to obtain better mercies; as ſome in asking temporall things, by that prayer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſpirituall mercies, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.2. Then they ſay, carnall men muſt not ſay, <hi>Lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from evill,</hi> becauſe they are never out of temptation. I anſwer, the godly are in the ſame condition, tempted either by the world, fleſh, or the devill, continually, and they cannot eſcape them all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, except they goe out of the world, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10, 11. then muſt they not pray and uſe the meanes to eſcape them. Then they ſay, carnall men are temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it ſelfe, but I ſay, how can that be? For as they are Gods creatures they are good, and not to be ſo called, and it is but their words and deeds that tempt, for their thoughts cannot, neither is it all their words and deeds, but ſome of them onely, and they have a naturall conſcience to oppoſe thoſe words and deeds that are tempting to others, and why may they not pray againſt them, then we ought not to diſcourage any, but rather teach them better, for God will deſtroy theſe families that call not on his name, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.25.</p>
               <p>But when they ſee that they cannot prevail with the godly to caſt away one part of this prayer, and the ungodly to caſt away all the reſt, then they bring ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments that no man living ought to ſay thoſe words of Chriſt for a prayer, firſt they ſay, it was not Chriſts Doctrine, that we ſhould ſay theſe words, but hee rather ſpake them to frame other Prayers by, for he ſayth, <hi>Pray after this manner. Mat.</hi> 6.9. I anſwer, although the manner and forme be there taught by Chriſt, yet this hinders not, but theſe words may be uſed as a Prayer, as a juſt weight or meaſure may ſerve for our preſent uſe, to wey or meaſure any thing by, and yet ſerve for a pattern to make another by, ſo this Prayer may be a pattern of true Prayer, and yet we may uſe the very words of at in prayer, as we doe many of <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalmes to praiſe God with, except they deny all Scripture words to be uſed as Prayer, and if they doe not, why ſhould this Scripture bee denyed, and when Chriſt ſayth, <hi>after this manner pray,</hi> we may as well ſay them <hi>verbatim,</hi> after him, as a ſcholler may ſay his leſſon <hi>verbatim</hi> after his Maſter.</p>
               <p n="2">2 They ſay <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Luke</hi> have not the ſame forme, nor the ſame words nor the ſame number of them, therefore not to be ſaid as a prayer. I anſwer, we doe not contend that the ſame words in the Lords Prayer muſt of neceſſity always be uſed and no other, but we hold it lawfull to uſe thoſe words of Chriſt as a Prayer, either as it is recorded by <hi>Matthew</hi> or by <hi>Luke,</hi> or if we ſay them <hi>verbatim</hi> after the one, it is no offence to the other, and if we varie in phraſe from both, it is no offence to either, onely we hold that the ſame words, or to the ſame purpoſe, may be uſed by us as a prayer.</p>
               <p n="3">3 They ſay, all the circumſtances of Chriſt in both the Evangeliſts, doth but teach us how to uſe Prayer aright, and he doth teach us the right uſe of almeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deedes and faſtings, which is to avoid ambition, hypocriſie, and babling, and the like, and how to come to God in prayer, as children to their parents, ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bread or fiſh, or an egg, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.1.18. and to make our requeſts
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113584:22"/>unto God for our particular wants in faith and love. I Anſwer, the ſaying of theſe words <hi>verhatom</hi> which Chriſt, hath taught us make us guilty of ambition, hypocriſie, and babling: and in the uſe of theſe words cannot we come to God with feeling of our particular wants, as children to their fathers, and in the uſe of them cannot we practice faith and love, they ſay theſe things, but they cannot prove them, and till then we deny them. but will they condemne all the Saints of God that uſe this prayer to be ambitious hypocrites and bablers, and without feeling of their particular wants, and without faith and love. theſe be but uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable ſlanders without any proofe.</p>
               <p n="4">4 They ſay, that the Apoſtles which knew the minde of Chriſt did neither binde themſelves to theſe words nor others, but ſtill prayed according to their ſeverall occaſions, as in <hi>Act.</hi> 1.24, 25.4.24 30. I Anſwer, although they did not ſo binde themſelves to theſe words yet it will not follow, that they never uſed the ſame words as a prayer, and beſides, they might goe by this rule upon ſeverall occaſions, for although we doe not finde that they did teach any to ſay over the Lords Prayer, yet they uſed ſet formes of prayer in their ſalutations, for ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> it is the token in every Epiſtle, ſo I wright <hi>The grace of cur Lord Jeſus Chriſt be with you all, Amen</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3 17, 18. then is it unlawfull to uſe the forme of words which Chriſt hath taught us, and yet lawfull for them to uſe their own forme for a prayer, and yet they taught men according to their occaſions and neceſſities to make their requeſts known to God, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6. then I ſay they muſt uſe the prayer of Chriſt, for it doth not hinder ſupplication in the ſpirit, although they were not always tyed to ſay thoſe very words in their prayers.</p>
               <p n="5">5 They ſay, to pray in a ſtrange tongue, the unlearned know not what they ſay, <hi>Then how ſhall they ſay Amen?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.16. But ſay they, this Prayer they knew, and would ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> though it were ſpoken in a ſtrange tongue, therefore they did not uſe it in any Language. I Anſwer, they might uſe the Prayer often at <hi>Corinth</hi> and yet the unlearned not able to ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> becauſe there was extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Prophets, and ſomtimes they ſpake ſtrange languages by a ſpeciall giſt at ſuch a time, the unlearned could not underſtand them, as at the end to ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> therefore <hi>Paul</hi> bids them pray in that language, that the people might joyne with them in their prayers, but ſuppoſe, they ſeldome uſed this in ſtrange Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, this might cauſe them not to underſtand it, and yet this is not ſufficient to prove that they hold it unlawfull to uſe it as a prayer, but ſuppoſe the unlearned heard them often to ſay it, yet they could not ſay Amen to it, unleſſe they had a diſtinct underſtanding of the ſeverall words therein, that their hearts and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons might goe along with him that ſaid it, and in the concluſion witneſſe their conſent by ſaying <hi>Amen</hi> to it. Again, if the people when they underſtand it may ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to it, is it unlawfull, or dare they ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to an unlawfull prayer which is not ſupplication in the ſpirit, nor made in the feeling of their wants, nor in faith and love, and if they may lawfully ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> at the concluſion then without all queſtion it may be ſaid as a Prayer.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:113584:22"/>
               <p n="6">6 They ſay, If Chriſt hath commanded to uſe theſe words in that number and order, then they ſin that pray at any time and uſe not theſe words, for ſaith hee, <hi>When you pray, ſay Our Father, &amp;c.</hi> I Anſwer, this command of Chriſt ſheweth that he allows the uſe of theſe words, in the ſame number and order, that either <hi>Matthew</hi> or <hi>Luke</hi> hath recorded, yet it doth not follow that we are tyed to thoſe very words alone, and to no other in our prayers: ſuppoſe a man ſend his ſervant on a meſſage to his friend, and command him to ſay to him ſuch words <hi>verbatim,</hi> after this manner, or to the ſame purpoſe, then ſhall that ſervant be counted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull or diſobedient, if he uſe the very words without any change, or if he ſpeak to the ſame purpoſe, when Chriſt ſent out his Apoſtles he gave them a prayer for ſalutation, when they came to any houſe to ſay, <hi>peace be to this houſe, Luke</hi> 10.5. thereby to warrant them that they might uſe thoſe very words <hi>verbatim,</hi> or the ſame for ſubſtance, and either way obey the command of Chriſt, ſo the Lord taught a forme of praiſe to ſay alway, <hi>the Lord be praiſed, Pſal.</hi> 40.16. this doth allow us to uſe the ſame words, or the ſame for ſubſtance in other words, ſo here the Lords prayer may be uſed as the ſame for ſubſtance, and both ways his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is fulfilled, but they ſtand much upon this word, <hi>when you pray,</hi> as if it were always to be uſed when we pray, but they are miſtaken, for ſayth Chriſt, <hi>When thou makeſt a feaſt call not thy friends, and when thou makeſt a feaſt call the poor and mamed, Luke</hi> 12.12, 13. But doth this tie us never to feaſt our friends, and always to feaſt the poor and the maimed, when the devill is caſt out he ſaith, <hi>I will return, Luke</hi> 11.24. but when the devill was caſt out did he likewiſe returne, ſeven de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils was caſt out of <hi>Mary Magdelen,</hi> and a legion of Devils out of another, but did they return, if not, then this word, <hi>when you pray,</hi> doth extend it ſelfe to all our prayers, but then they ſay, if we be tyed to theſe words, it will exclude in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward deſires to be prayers, but I ſay again, we are not always tyed to ſay thoſe words, although we may ſomtimes uſe them, and yet we may pray acceptably without any words or voices at all, as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Hannah</hi> did, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.15. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.13.</p>
               <p n="7">7 They ſay that forme of prayer doth plainly and fully direct and reſtrain our ignorant and inordinate deſires unto certain heads in which whatſoever is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and lawfull to be asked I anſwer, although all things needfull to be asked, be contained in the words of this prayer, and thouſands of petitions more may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from it by Gods people, according to their ſeverall occaſions, yet it will not follow that the words of this Prayer may not be uſed as a prayer: Again, to ſay the heads are ſo generall, that no man can rightly apply them to his particular occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions itſelfe for in generall reſpect and love to Gods name, and Kingdom, and will, we may lawfully uſe theſe words in prayer, although for the preſent our thoughts doe not ſettle upon that particular way and means by which his name may be ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, and his will accompliſhed, ſo the Angels wait with reverence, and with a general reſpect to Gods wil, before they have any particular ſpecial comand how to do it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.10. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.20. ſo Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:113584:23"/>a generall reſpect of our ſelves to bee forgiven, and with a generall reſpect of temptations and afflictions to bee delivered from, although for the preſent wee think of no particular ſins or temptations, if this were not ſo, it were unlawful for <hi>Paul</hi> to pray at all, when as hee knew nothing by himſelfe, yet ſayth hee, <hi>I</hi> am not hereby juſtified, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. and <hi>David</hi> prayed to be clenſed from ſecret ſins, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. and although thoſe words be generall, yet they may have relation to particular ſins and temptations, and to particular meanes to glorifie God, but neither, man nor Church can be in ſuch condition, as to reach all things needfull for all perſons, and all occaſions as thoſe heads comprehend.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, ſuppoſe no man nor churches caſe can reach unto all things compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in this prayer, yet theſe words concerne every Chriſtian, then they may uſe it as a prayer, and if we ſhould reject this prayer, becauſe our condition can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reach all things contained in it: by this argument we may caſt away all prayers, bleſſings and ſalutations in the Scriptures, for if we ſay, <hi>Peace be unto you, Luke</hi> 10.5. <hi>The Lord bleſſe you Ruth</hi> 2.4. Who can reach all things comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in theſe ſentences, for they contain the whole covenant of grace, with all the fruits and benefits of it, then we may uſe it as a prayer, although wee cannot reach all things that are comprehended in it.</p>
               <p n="8">8 They ſay, if theſe words of Chriſt be uſed as a prayer, as well may Miniſters at the end of their Sermons, and Magiſtrates at the end of their Inſtructions and Exhortations, ſay over the ten Commandements, becauſe they doe fully compriſe all duties.</p>
               <p>I Anſwer, our queſtion onely about the lawfulneſſe, and not about the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of uſing it as a prayer: we doe not ſay that Miniſters are bound to ſay over the Lords Prayer at the end of every Sermon, nor Magiſtrates at the end of every inſtruction or exhortation: but ſuppoſe Miniſters at the end of every Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſhould ſay over the ten Cmmandements, as formerly they have done upon the Lords day before Catechiſing, and that Magiſtrates at the end of ſolemne exhortations ſhould repeat the ten Commandements, this would rather bee a teſtimony of their obedience to Gods Laws rather then to be any tranſgreſſion of it: again, there is no equality in this compariſon, for the Lord in his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, hath in his word taught us ſhort forms of prayer for ſalutation, in two or three words, becauſe we have every day many occaſions to uſe them, and ſo wee have of mutuall exhortations; then what an abſurd thing would it be to conclude every ſalutation and exhortation with the Lords Prayer and ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, it may be a hundred times in a week, yet this will not prove it to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull to begin or conclude a ſolemne exerciſe in a Church o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> family, with the Lords Prayer or ten Commandements.</p>
               <p n="9">9 They ſay this Prayer of Chriſt is a moſt perfect forme, wherein is no want or ſuperfluity, then if this be the meaning of Chriſt to ſay over thoſe words in prayer to God, then we ought only to uſe this and no other: For (ſay they) if we do, it is
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113584:23"/>babling and preſumption to put any other words in ſteed of this prayer, that is ſo abſolute, perfect and ſufficient, and the Lord will be worſhipped with the beſt we have, <hi>and he is accurſed that hath a male in his flocke, and yet doth offer to the Lord a corrupt thing, Malachie</hi> 1.14. I anſwer, God doth not denounce that curſe upon thoſe that do not offer the beſt they have in ſacrifice, but againſt thoſe that offered corrupt things contrary to the Law, <hi>Levit.</hi> 1.3.10. But this chiefly croſteth Hypocrites, who pretend that they love God, when they doe not; but for a man that had a Kow and two ſheep, <hi>Eſay</hi> 7.22. He was not required to offer his Kow, becauſe ſhe was the beſt that he had: or if a man had ten ſheep, hee was not bound to offer the beſt of them, onely the Law required it <hi>ſhould be without blemiſh, and then he might take the tenth as they paſſe under the rod, Levit.</hi> 27.32, 33. Then, if this Text prove any thing to caſt away all other Prayers, but this of Chriſt, then they muſt prove them all, but this to be corrupt things, like the torne and lame ſacrifice: for although this prayer of Chriſt be more excellent then any of ours, yet this will not nullifie and make ours void, no more then the excellency of one ſacrifice will make void another that hath not the ſame degree of goodneſſe in it: yet this is beſide our controverſie, for hitherto they have argued, that it was unlawfull to uſe this prayer of Chriſt at all as a prayer: and now they ſeem to argue, that all other are unlawfull but this prayer of Chriſt, becauſe it is ſo perfect and ſufficient, that there is neither want nor ſuperfluity in it, and yet before they ſaid, there was ſo much ſuperfluity in it, that neither man nor Churches caſe could reach it, and therefore they ſaid, it was not lawfull to ſay it for a prayer, and another time they ſaid, it was too ſhort to reach all mens conditions and occaſions, and therefore unlawfull to uſe it as a prayer. Thus wee ſee their arguing is meere caviling and not to be regarded of thoſe that love the truth, and thoſe words of Chriſt may be bleſſed as a prayer, notwithſtanding all their cavils made againſt it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:113584:24"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>This Chapter contains a Diſputation with the Anabaptiſts, about the Magiſtrates power, in commanding thoſe of a contrary judgment to conforme with us in our publike worſhip, or to puniſh them in caſe of refuſall.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THey ſay, if a Magiſtrate command thoſe of a contrary judgment to conforme with them this would make them ſin againſt their conſcience as Hypocrites, I anſwered, that to come to the publike Aſſemblies is from the Magiſtrate, but to be Hypocrites is from themſelves, as when a man ſpurs his horſe, if he go it is from the man, but if he halt it is from himſelfe, then the cauſe of hypocriſie is in your ſelves, and not in our godly Magiſtrates for commanding you to come to our publike Aſſemblies. Again, they command, but the outward man as his words and actions, and his bodily preſence there, but they have no law can reach their conſcience to command it, nor to inflict any puniſhment upon it, in caſe of refuſall, it is God that requires truth in the inward parts, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.6. <hi>and to obey from the heart, Rom.</hi> 6.17. <hi>For he ſees not as man ſees, he looks on the heart,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7. if they be hypocrites, it is for want of ſyncere obedience to God from the heart, but if they bring thoſe excuſes to the Aſſembly, they have done all that the Magiſtrate commands them, then they do not make ſome Hypocrites, but ſuppoſe, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding theſe of a contrary judgment ſhould accidentally make them hypocrites; yet ſo far as they obey, they ſhall loſe nothing by it: if they obey outwardly, they may by that receiv bleſſings, as <hi>Ahab</hi> did, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.29. <hi>The judgment was removed from his days, and the Phariſees had a reward, Mat.</hi> 6, 5. But thoſe that obey from the heart ſhall receive ſpirituall and eternall bleſſings, <hi>For every one ſhall receive according to his works, Pſal.</hi> 62.12. <hi>Job</hi> 34.11. though not meritorious for it, yet according to it, whether it be done in hypocriſie or in truth; then is it not better to conforme in outward obedience to obtain outward bleſſings, then to be both mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable here and hereafter: and ſhall we blame them that ſeek to pull us out of any danger, and to procure for us, although but outward bleſſings. Again, it is better to ſin in uſing the meanes tending to ſalvation, then to ſin in that way <hi>that takes Lold on hell, Prov.</hi> 7. For if you caſt off Magiſtrates authority, you will in time kill the Saints of God, and thinke in your conſcience that you doe God good ſervice, <hi>John</hi> 16.2. then bring your conſcienc to the word, and not the word to your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, leſt you exalt your conſcience above the word. Again, when all are brought to the means of ſalvation, it may pleaſe God to make thoſe means effectuall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the poſts of wiſdomes doores they ſhall be bleſſed, and to the poole they ſhall be cured.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:113584:24"/>
               <p>Now I ſhall prove that Magiſtrates have power to command thoſe of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary judgment to conforme with us in publike worſhip; or to puniſh in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> refuſe to obey ſuch lawes as ſhall be made for the preſerving of peace both in Church and State, this they have good warrant from Scripture, for King <hi>Aſs. comanded Judah to ſeek the Lord God of their Pathers &amp; to doe the Law and Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and Jehoſhaphat ſent Princes, and with them Levits to teach in Judah, &amp; reformed government in matiers of the Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 14.4.17.7, 8 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.11. <hi>And Manaſſes commanded Judah to ſerve the Lord, and they kept the Paſſeover ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the comandement of King Joſias, Chap.</hi> 31.4.35.16. Here then it is plain that Magiſtrates have power to command obedience to the publike worſhip of God in relation to the Church, now we ſhall ſee their power to puniſh thoſe that are diſobedient the Lord ſaid to <hi>Moſes, Take the heads of the people and hang them up before the Sun, that bowed down to the gods of Moab, Numb.</hi> 25.2, 3.4. <hi>And Ioaſh ordained, that if any man did plead for Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, he ſhould be put to death, Iudg.</hi> 6.31, <hi>And Aſa puniſhed his own mother for having an Idoll in a Grove,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 13. <hi>And when Iehu deſtroyed Baal out of Iſrael, with all his prieſts and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, the Lord ſaid, Thou heſt done well in executing that which was right in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> own eyes,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 10.28, 30. <hi>And Ioſiaſh put down the Idol <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, yea, bee ſlue all the prieſts of the high places, and burnt their bones upon their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.5, 20. Thus they may ſee that Magiſtrates had this power to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand obedience to the publike worſhip of God, and to puniſh the diſobedient, and if they have loſt this power, let them prove when and how they come to loſe it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the <hi>Iews</hi> had the ſame Law of God contained in the ten Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements as we have, and they had the ſame Goſpel as we, for ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell was preached to <hi>Abraham, Gal.</hi> 3.8. and <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>For this cauſe war the Goſpell peached to them that are dead,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.6. onely it was to them in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> types and ſhadows, and to us more clcerly manifeſted, yet they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by the ſame Chriſt as we, for there is but one way to heaven. <hi>Ier.</hi> 32.39. Then why <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not our Magiſtrates have the ſame authority in relation to the Church as they had, but this man denied that the <hi>Iews</hi> had the Goſpel, or that faith was of abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity for ſalvation, flat againſt the Scripture, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.16 19, 36. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. but they having found out ſome new way contrary to the old and good way, <hi>in which our fathers walked and were not confounded, Pſal.</hi> 22. They muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> have new Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, with leſſe authority in relation to the Church, to command obedience to the publike worſhip of God, or to puniſh the oppoſers of it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, if Magiſtrates under the olde Teſtament had this power, then much more now under the New, becauſe now they have greater obligation to command obedience, and to puniſh the oppoſers of it then they had, becauſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113584:25"/>The Covenant of grace is now more manifeſt then it was to the Jews, and if our Magiſtrates had not that power, which the Magiſtrates in the old Teſtament had, our church would not be in ſo ſafe a condition now, as it was under the Old Teſtament.</p>
               <p>Fourthly. Kings and Queens muſt be as nurſing fathers and mothers to the Church, <hi>Eſay</hi> 49.22. but ſhall Kings and Queens have no authority about the Church when they lend their power to aſſiſt it, and ſhall fathers and mothers have no command in relation to the Church? and ſhall nurſes have no power to feed their children? <hi>Jehoſhophat</hi> ſent Miniſters to teach in <hi>Judah,</hi> and ſayth the Lord, <hi>Cyrus</hi> is my ſheepherd, then ſhall not he defend the Church as a ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd doth his flock? <hi>David</hi> fed them according to the integrity of his heart, and guided them by the skilfulneſſe of his hands, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.72. but while the Lord looks for a man to make up the hedge, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.30. and ſaith, he ſhall be called the repairer of the breach, <hi>Eſay</hi> 58.12. In the meane time, theſe men throw open the gap to the ravening lyon, which ſhews how inſufferable they are in any Chriſtian Church, yea, they be but like vipers, both to Church and State.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Princes in Scripture are called Saviours to <hi>Sion,</hi> and ſuch are foretold to be in our dayes, <hi>Obad.</hi> 21. But how can they be Saviours to our Church, when they muſt neither command obedience, nor puniſh thoſe that oppoſe it, but God commands to puniſh thoſe that intiſe others to Idolatry, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.6. if they doe not, they are guilty of other mens ſins, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. and they carry the Sword in vain, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. and God will have ſomthing againſt them for ſuffering <hi>Jezabel</hi> to ſeduce the ſervants of God, and for ſuffering the doctrine of <hi>Baalam,</hi> and the doctrine of the <hi>Nicolaitans</hi> which God hates, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.14, 15, 20. The very Heathens will puniſh thoſe that oppoſe their Religion, and ſhall not Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtrates doe as much for the true Religion as they doe for a falſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, We are commanded to pray for Kings, and all thoſe in authority, that we may leade a quiet and a peaceable life in all godlineſſe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3. But if they have no power in relation to the Church, to command obedience, and to puniſh the oppoſers of it, then what a vain prayer would this be? but hee that rules over men muſt bee juſt, and not onely ſo, but ruling in the feare of God, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.3. <hi>I know,</hi> ſayth the Lord, <hi>that Abraham my friend, will command his houſhold to doe judgment and juſtice, Gen.</hi> 18. <hi>And we muſt obey for conſcience ſake, Rom.</hi> 13.7. but not bringing the conſcience in obedience to mans precepts, but we muſt obey men in conſcience of obedience unto God that commands it. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1. Then let them take heed how they deſpiſe government.</p>
               <p>But then becauſe the Magiſtrates power is a burthen to this man, and he would fain eaſe himſelfe of it, therefore he propounded ſome Queries.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Hee would know, whether the whole ground of the Jews worſhip, for
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113584:25"/>matter and forme, was not in plain precepts and commandements, and taught them by the Prophets, as they had immediately received it of the Lord, to this I grant affirmatively that it was ſo, but then hee would know, whether any Ruler, Governour, or King of <hi>Judah</hi> either did, or lawfully might ſet up, alter, or change either matter or forme of that worſhip, and to compel the people to obey it, or to inflict a penalty upon any in caſe of diſobedience: I anſwer negatively, that no King of <hi>Judah</hi> did or ought to ſet up, alter, or change, either matter or forme of Gods publike worſhip, yet the Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> both did and ought to command obedience to that matter, and to that forme of publike worſhip, that was ſet up and received from the Prophets, as they received it from the Lord, and alſo they both did and ought to puniſh thoſe that were diſobedient to that forme that was ſet up by the Lord, as all thoſe Scriptures before quoted witneſſe, and ſo our Magiſtrates may and ought to compell obedience to the outward forme of the worſhip of God in relation to the Church, although their power be not in the Church or over the Church, but onely aſſiſtant to the Church, then they may command obedience to it, and puniſh thoſe that deſpiſe or abuſe it, yet I grant they never had nor ſhall have power to alter the forme or matter, or to add any new matter to it, nor take any matter from it, this belongs to Chriſt alone, the head and King of the Church, but I ſay again, that Magiſtrates have power to command outward obedience to that forme that Chriſt hath ſet up, neither may the matter of any ordinance be taken away or changed, or new inventions of our own added to them, and ſo for the matter of the Sacraments, wee muſt neither take away the bread nor the wine, nor add any thing elſe, and ſo likewiſe for the perſons, the ſubject matter of the Church, they muſt be the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> neither may a Turke be admitted, unleſſe hee will leave his Turkiſh Religion, he is not fit matter for it, yet all this hinders not, but Chriſtian Magiſtrates may command Chriſtians being already in the Church to obedience, and to puniſh thoſe that are diſobedient to the Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2 He would know whether the Jews government now under the Goſpel per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to Gentiles any more then the matter and forme of the worſhip, and if their government, why not all, both the Church and State, and if all, whether the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of any be not under the curſe, eſpecially ſo much as is under the letter of the Law. I anſwer, the Jews Government both in Church and State, as it was the Judiciall Law, it ought to be obeyed of none but Jews onely, and as much as their Law was but ceremoniall, the matter was calves and lambs, and the Altar and Temple, and the forme was ſacrifices, and divers waſhings, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But now Chriſt the King of the Church is come, hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath taken away much of the matter and forme of their publike worſhip, and now all Kings and Rulers being his deputies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt give their power to the Church, to defend that matter
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113584:26"/>and forme that Chriſt the King of it hath ſet up, and appointed to be themat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and forme of it, but while hee pleads for the Jews matter and forme hee ſmells rank of Judaiſme, yet it is like the Jews when they are called may have their own poſitive Laws for their own Common-wealth, as our poſitive Law is the Law of <hi>England,</hi> But wee are no more bound to the Jews poſitive laws, then they are bound to our poſitive Laws, although thoſe are written in the Word, and ours are not, but beſides the ceremoniall law that ended by Chriſt, and the Judiciall law that was made particularly for Jews, they had alſo the eternall morall law, and what their Magiſtrates did in obedience to that, our Kings and Magiſtrates are bound to the ſame as well as they, and it was in obedience to that law, that they commanded uniformity in publike worſhip, and puniſhed the diſobedient, and further I ſay, that our poſitive laws binde our Magiſtrates and people as ſtrongly being grounded on the morall law, being the law of nature, as the Jews poſitive laws bound them, although theirs was written in the Word, and ours are not.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, He would know whether the matter and forme of the worſhip of God under the Goſpel, lies not in as plain precepts and commandements as the matter and forme of the Jews worſhip, and whether to urge and compell men to any other be not ſin.</p>
               <p>Here I ſhall firſt grant, that the matter and forme now, is in as plain precepts and commandements as the Jewes was, and to compell men to any other is ſin. But here lies not our controverſie, for our Magiſtrates neither command other things then CHRIST hath appointed to bee the ſubject matter of the Church, although themſelves, moſt abominably, brought a Cat to the Sacrament. Neither doe wee admit Infidels or Turks unleſſe they leave their Religion, and become Chriſtians, neither doe wee take away the bread or the wine, or change them, or add any thing elſe to them, not doe we take away or change any other ordinance, but themſelves have caſt away much of the ſubject matter of the Church being eſteemed of them but as reprobates, although many of them be the deare children of GOD, unleſſe they pleaſe then humours, and they have caſt away the Ordinance of ſinging of Pſalmes, and all family inſtructions, admonitions, prayers, watchings over one another in love, and building up one another in faith. Thus they have almoſt caſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y both matter and forme of the true viſible Church, when as they cannot ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e us as wanting any Ordinance, nor of having any ſuperſluous of our own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing.</p>
               <p>Then if Magiſtrates ſhould command any other matter or forme, they would ſinne in to doing, yet it will not follow that when Magiſtrates com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the ſame that CHRIST hath ſet up that then they ſhould ſinne.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:113584:26"/>The Lord ſaid to <hi>Moſes',</hi> The Magiſtrate gather the people together, both men, women, and children, and the ſtranger that is within the gates, that they may heare, and that they may learne, and feare the LORD thy GOD, and obſerve to doe all the words of this Law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.12. and ſaith Chriſt compell them to come in, that my houſe may be filled, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.23. then I hope it will not trouble your conſciences to be compelled to heare the word, which is the onely way to know the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant between God and Chriſt in our nature, and when it is known, it will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>received, They that know thy name will truſt in thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.10. yet the Magiſtrates will not command you to believe they are not Lords of your faith, but they may be helpers of your joy, but ſaith is the gift of GOD, the Magiſtrate onely commands to come to the paths of wiſdoms doors that we may be bleſſed, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.33. this is the way to come in to the Covenant of Chriſt, the Lord of the Church, and when this is done, we need not make another Covenant with the members, as they d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e at <hi>New England,</hi> and if they were in Covenant with Chriſt, as they pretend the members neede not make ſuch ſoldering, for a Chriſtian hath right to all Churches, as well as to one Church, and needs not way<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for the members ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mttance, although their Lordly pride beſuch, while they pretend humility, that they will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of it.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, he would know whether any people under heaven have power to frame the outward government of the Church ſo perfectly, that it ſhall neither have ſin nor failing in it, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not then ſaith he where is there power to command obedience to that which is ſinful. I anſwer, It is true, none have power to frame ſuch a govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that hath neither ſin nor failings in it, therefore the Parliament doth not take upon them to frame any government for the Church, becauſe as I ſaid before, their power is not in the Church, nor over the Church, but in relation to the Church, as lending their power to aſſiſt it, therefore they have called the aſſembly of Divines to ſearch the Scripture, to ſee what government Chriſt hath appointed for his Church, who is the Lord and King of it then there buſineſſe is onely to ſearch this our and then the Parlinment by a poſitive Law of the Land will command that this government ſhall be obſerved, and no other but when all the Aſſembly, or the greateſt part ſhall conclude upon one way of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and the Parliament hath eſtabliſhed that Government by a Law of the Kingdom then I ſay, although there ſhall be ſome failings in it, yet it being as neer the rule as all our Divines upon diligent ſearch can finde out, and the Parlian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent hath made it a Statute to bee obſerved, it muſt bee obeyed, and all thoſe Scriptures and Reaſons before alledged ſerve to confirme it, and thoſe that will not, doe the Law of GOD, and the Law of the King, let
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:113584:27"/>judgement be executed ſpeedily upon him, whether it be to death or baniſhment, confiſcation of goods, or impriſonment, <hi>Ezra.</hi> 7.25, 26. and then it will be but a weake excuſe to renounce a poſitive Law of the Land upon this ground, ſaying, It is not perfect without ſin or failing, therefore I will not obey it, by this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they may renounce all our Laws and Magiſtrates, for no humane Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance nor Magiſtrate can be without ſin or failing, then, by their argument, both muſt be caſt away, and ſo live like ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> without any government, but this ſhews how unſufferable that faction is, to be among Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe, they ſhould have free leave to frame their own government, what they would have, upon condition it ſhould be confirmed by an act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, I am confident they would not agree to have it done, becauſe they all ſeeke to have a gap open to turne to what Hereſie they pleaſe, This alſo ſhews how unſufferable they be amongſt us. But ſuppoſe they were willing to have ſuch a government eſtabliſhed as they ſhould like of, then I would know why a whole aſſembly of faithfull, learned, wiſe, godly, and pious men ſhould be deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that which they will grant to a few, and ſome of them factious; and others hereticall, nay, why will they not grant our Aſſembly ſo much as they grant to one ſingle man, who ſetteth up what government he pleaſeth, and they all freely obey him, when he aymes at his own ends, to gather Churches that he may vent his Hereſie and faction, which is a thing to be abhorred of all godly Chriſtians, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more enſlaved to him then ever they were to the Prelates, if they had but eyes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſee it. The meane time all may ſee how theſe men deſpiſe the Magiſtrates pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in relation to the Church, when they command obedience to it, or puniſh the oppoſers of it.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:113584:27"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
